<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An exposition vpon the CXII. Psalme The high way to euerlasting blessednesse. Written for the benefit of Gods church, by T.S.</title>
            <author>Stint, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1621</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 202 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 110 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12974</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23269</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107442</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843143</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843143</idno>
            <idno type="VID">7856</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12974)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7856)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 586:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An exposition vpon the CXII. Psalme The high way to euerlasting blessednesse. Written for the benefit of Gods church, by T.S.</title>
                  <author>Stint, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 204 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Bernard Alsop dwelling in Distaffe Lane at the signe of the Dolphin,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1621.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>T.S. = Thomas Stint.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalm 112 --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:7856:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7856:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN EXPOSITION VPON THE CXII. Pſalme.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The high way to euerlaſting bleſſedneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Written for the benefit of Gods Church, by <hi>T. S.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 111.10.</bibl> The feare of the Lord is the beginning of wiſedome, a good vnderſtanding haue al they that do his Commandements.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.13.</bibl> Therefore let vs feare the end of all, feare God, and keepe his Commandements, for this is the whole duty of man.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Bernard Alſop</hi> dwelling in Diſtaffe Lane at the Signe of the Dolphin. 1621.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:7856:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7856:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT worſhipfull, right vertuous, truly religious and moſt worthy Miſtres M. <hi>Murry,</hi> wife to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Mr. <hi>Thomas Murry</hi> Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary to the Prince his highneſſe, the <hi>encreaſe of grace, and all true hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines externall, internall, eternall.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>RIght Worſhipfull, the principall thing of which I reade in holy Scriptures which makes vs both acceptable to God, &amp; approued of the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, is the grace of regeneration, &amp; to become new creatures, this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, when all other things faile, commends vs to God, this diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſheth the good from the bad,
<pb facs="tcp:7856:3"/> the precious from the vile, the godly from the wicked: this grace Right worſhipfull, as being of all others moſt requiſite, I moſt wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly commend to your wiſe and Chriſtian Conſideration, hauing experience of your Chriſtian loue. The authour of this Pſalme was bleſſed <hi>Dauid</hi> the ſweet ſinger of Iſrael, wherein the Prophet tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches vs the way to true bleſſednes, that is, to feare God and delight in his Commandements, for cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion is nothing,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 7.29</note> and vncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, is nothing, but the kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of the Commandements of God, I may truly ſay of this new creature,<note place="margin">Prou. 31.29</note> as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſpeaketh of the vertuous woman, many are the graces of Gods ſpirit, but this excels them all.</p>
            <p>This is it indeede which will make you thriſe bleſſed, both of
<pb facs="tcp:7856:3"/> God and all good men, for the kingdome of God is not meate &amp; drinke, but righteouſneſſe, peace,<note place="margin">Rom. 14.17 18.</note> and ioy in the holy ghoſt, and hee that in theſe things ſerueth God is acceptable to him,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 2.30</note> and approo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of men, they that thus honor God, hee will honour, whereas thoſe that deſpiſe him neglecting the meanes of regeneration, ſhall be lightly eſteemed, for there is no reſpect of perſons with God, but be hee what he will be, noble or ignoble, in euery nation, he that feareth God,<note place="margin">Act 10.35.</note> and worketh righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, is accepted with him. Firſt therefore ſeeke the kingdom of God and his righteouſneſſe, and all other things (as honour,<note place="margin">Mat. 6.33.</note> wealth, and riches) ſhall bee caſt vpon you, namely, in the ſober vſe of lawfull meanes, this is the good and right way only to feare
<pb facs="tcp:7856:4"/> the Lord, and to ſerue him in truth with all our hearts:<note place="margin">1. Sam. 12.23.24.</note> by this ye ſhall be ſure to haue the honor that comes from God, as Chriſt ſayth,<note place="margin">Ioh. 12.26.</note> If any man ſerue me, him will my father honour; whereas on the contrary, without this we can neuer haue Gods approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, though wee may haue the worlds commendation, yea thogh the world, and all men in the world ſpeake wel of vs, we may be accurſed:<note place="margin">Luke 26.</note> Curſed are you when all men praiſe you; that is, if God diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praiſe you, and ye want his appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation and commendation. Woe be vnto you, though all men ſpeak well of you, and know it for your vnſpeakeable comfort,<note place="margin">Pſal. 4.3.</note> that you being godly, God ſetteth you a part for his owne ſelfe, all Gods delight is vppon the Saints on earth,<note place="margin">Pſal. 16.4.</note> and vpon ſuch as excell in
<pb facs="tcp:7856:4"/> vertue, the Lord taketh pleaſure in thoſe that feare him, the Lord ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth pleaſure in his people,<note place="margin">Pſal. 147. &amp; 149.4.</note> &amp; will beautifie the meeke with ſaluation and remember with ioy the words of God by <hi>Moſes,</hi> if wee heare Gods voyce indeed, with care &amp; conſcience to practiſe it, by liuing in faith, repentance, and new obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience,<note place="margin">Exod. 19.5.</note> you are Gods chiefe trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure aboue all people, though all the earth be his. Thus hoping for pardon of my boldneſſe, I intreat your fauourable acceptance and patronage hereof, &amp; humbly take my leaue, beſeeching Almighty God to bleſſe you &amp; yours, with the encreaſe of all bleſſings ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall and temporall, according to the many graces beſtowed vpon you. The Lord Ieſus Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and God, euen our Father, which hath loued vs, and hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
<pb facs="tcp:7856:5"/> vs euerlaſting conſolation, &amp; good hope through grace, eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh you in euery good word &amp; worke, the Lord fill you with all ſpirituall grace, that ſo you may be preſented moſt glorious with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſpot &amp; wrinkle in the Church triumphant, and that by our moſt bleſſed and alone Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt the righteous, to whom be glory and maieſtie, dominion and power, now and for euer, Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your worſhips ſeruant in all duty to be commanded</hi> T, S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:7856:5"/>
            <head>TO THE WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull vertuous and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Gentlewoman, and my appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued louing couſin, Miſtris <hi>Euelyen</hi> wife to the worſhipfull Maiſter <hi>Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard Euelyen</hi> Eſquire, one of his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Iuſtices of peace, in the county of Surry the encreaſe of all outward bleſſings and ſpiritual comforts, be multiplyed through Ieſus Chriſt.</head>
            <p>IT is a thing better knowne then well conſidered of, that in the myſticall body of Chriſt Ieſus, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery member hath his ſeuerall office, whereon it muſt attend, the weakeſt as well as the ſtrongeſt, and in the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily of the great ruler of heauen and earth, each ſeruant hath his ſeuerall
<pb facs="tcp:7856:6"/> talent, which hee muſt employ the meaneſt as well as the worthieſt, for want of greater abilitie, I haue done my beſt endeauour to ſhew the way to euerlaſting bleſſedneſſe, for the doing whereof, I had rather vndergoe the cenſures of ſuch as are curious, then depriue thoſe of a benefite that are religious and ſpiritually minded, perhaps I ſhall be toſſed by ſome with the ſtormy winds of euill cenſures, but for them I paſſe not, ſo I can be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit any: this part of the Pſalme I am ſure is excellent for the purpoſe, and <hi>Ierome</hi> doth call this booke of the Pſalmes, the treaſures of learning. Seeing therefore it was promiſed that vnder the kingdome of Chriſt, the meaneſt or leaſt ſhould bee like vnto <hi>Dauid,</hi> therefore trie your ſelfe if by grace you are partakers of Dauids di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſition, recorded in this Pſalme, you may be out of doubt that you ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:7856:6"/> be alſo partaker of his approbation, for the Lord is no accepter of perſons what he approues in one, he will alſo approue another; therfore follow <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> in the practiſe of Pietie, and then you ſhal be partaker of his praiſe which he receiued from God, the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall complaint of the world is, that there is no end of making many books becauſe there is little or no fruit in thoſe that reade them; but as the graſſe on the houſe top, which withers afore it commeth foorth, whereof the mower filleth not his hand,<note place="margin">Pſal. 129.6.</note> nor the gleaner his lap, neither they which goe by ſay, the bleſsing of the Lord be on you, we bleſſe you in the name of the Lord: therefore read to ſome purpoſe, that is, intend of a reader to become a doer, ſo ſhall you auert this curſe and reproch from you, ſo ſhall God and man call you bleſſed, and bleſſed ſhall you feele your ſelfe in ſo doing, now
<pb facs="tcp:7856:7"/> if you ſhall lay this to heart in the ſtrength of your yeares, it ſhall be your chiefeſt wiſedome, for it is religion and godlineſſe that ſhall embalme your name, and make it ſhine before men, and glorifie your ſoule amongſt Angels.<note place="margin">Luk. 7.37.</note> 
               <hi>Maries</hi> boxe of oyntment ſhall neuer be forgotten, for godlines hath the promiſe of this life, and that which is to come, and that without it there is no internall comfort to bee found in conſcience in this world, nor eternall happineſſe to bee hoped for in the next, hoping it ſhall finde entertainment at your hands, and that you will finde time at your lea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure to peruſe it deſiring your fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable acceptance of my good meaning in this behalfe, I humbly take my leaue, recommending you to the Lord, and to the word of his grace, the God of heauen ſo vouchſafe to water you and yours, with the dew of
<pb facs="tcp:7856:7"/> heauen, that with the godly man in this Pſalme your generation may bee bleſſed, and that at the end of this life your reward may be true bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which mercie the Lord grant you for his Sunne Ieſus Chriſts ſake, Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt bounden and in all Chriſtian duties to command, <hi>T. S.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:7856:8"/>
            <head>Faults eſcaped in Printing.</head>
            <p>Page. 21. line 8. reade chearefull. p. 27. l. 7. r. q.d. p. 29. l. 1 r. dans. p. 30. l. 18. r. in order. p. 36. l. 16. r. late. p. 81. l. 10. r. a to. p. 81. l. 14. r. vnto. p. 103. l. 23. r. heare. p. 104. l. 22. r. the Se<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chemites p. 125. l. 22. r. to do. p. 151. l. 7. r. of the Hebrewes. p 157. l. 4. r. that. p. 165. l. 8. r. in theſe. p. 187. l. 14. r. this the.</p>
            <p>Chriſtian Reader, I feare there are other faults beſides theſe, I deſire thee therefore to correct theſe and beare with the reſt, and ſo I bid the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> heartily farewell.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="exposition">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:7856:8"/>
            <head>AN EXPOSITION ON THE CXII. Pſalme. verſe 1.2.</head>
            <div n="1" type="verse">
               <epigraph>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>VERSE 1.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <q>Bleſſed is the man that feareth the Lord, and delighteth greatly in his commandements, his ſeed ſhall bee mighty vpon earth, the generation of the righteous ſhall be bleſſed.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THere is no greater encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement or ſtronger mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to ſtirre a man to an eager and earneſt purſuite of the meanes, then to propoſe vnto
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:7856:9"/> him an end; wherein at length his heart may repoſe, as in a concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of al comforts and content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: to which there is no poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of attainment, but by pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of heart, holineſſe of life, conſtancie in the courſe of ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification, which onely leade vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the face and preſence of God, where, and with whom alone, is the higheſt perfection of bliſſe, a riuer of infinite pleaſures, the well of life, and endleſſe reſt of all created deſires. For the capacitie of mans ſoule cannot poſſibly be filled with the ſufficiency of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny creatures, no not with a world of creatures: for they are all no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the worth of a mans ſoule: Chriſt himſelfe hauing pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred it in valuation: <hi>What ſhall it profit a man, though he ſhould winne the whole world, if he looſe his owne
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:7856:9"/> ſoule?</hi> And therefore can neuer be free from motion and vexation, vntill it reach vnto (either in cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine hope, or actuall fruition) an obiect; infinite, as well in excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of nature as duration of time. Bleſſed then was the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the diſpoſer of theſe heauenly ſongs of <hi>Dauid.</hi> Firſt, this Pſalme doth teach vs theſe two worthy points; namely, how the bleſſed man liues, and that is in the feare of the Lord. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, what manner of life he leades, <hi>and greatly delighteth in his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe Pſalms of <hi>Dauid</hi> the ſweet ſinger of Iſrael, are penned with ſuch heauenly wiſedome, that they are convenient for the ſtate of the whole Church, and euery member thereof. It is a banquet of heauenly wiſedome ſaith <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe;</hi>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:7856:10"/> and as <hi>Baſil</hi> ſpeakes of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther part of the Scripture likening it to an Apothecaries ſhop; ſo may this booke of the Pſalmes fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be compared: in which are ſo many ſundry ſorts of medicines, that euery man may haue that which is conuenient for his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe; for there is no ſickeneſſe of man, whereunto the booke of the Pſalmes furniſheth not a preſent remedy.</p>
               <p>Firſt, this bleſſed ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is deſcribed, ſhewing what hee doth carefully embrace and follow: <hi>Bleſſed is the man that feareth the Lord,</hi> that is, that endeauors to the vtmoſt of his power to liue in the feare of the Lord.</p>
               <p>Secondly, what is his practiſe; namely, to be much &amp; often in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious &amp; Chriſtian meditation; <hi>and delights greatly in his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:7856:10"/>
               <p>Thirdly, he ſheweth the happy ſucces of this bleſſed man, <hi>his ſeed ſhall be mighty vpon earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now ſeeing this is the maine propoſition of the pſalm, to proue that the godly man, and hee that feares the Lord is onely bleſſed; therefore the Prophet doth firſt ſhew who bee truely bleſſed, and then wherein their bleſſedneſſe doth conſiſt. <hi>Dauid</hi> often vſeth this phraſe as in the firſt Pſalm; <hi>Bleſſed is the man that walketh not in the councell of the vngodly, &amp;c.</hi> And in the 32. Pſalme; <hi>Bleſſed is hee whoſe wickedneſſe is forgiuen, whoſe ſinnes is couered, &amp;c.</hi> And as here we haue it: <hi>Bleſſed is the man that feareth the Lord.</hi> It ſeems to be the words of a man in admiration or admiring with himſelfe, as if he ſhould ſay, O the bleſſedneſſe of that man that feareth the Lord.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:7856:11"/>
               <p>In this duty I obſerue three points; firſt, what is the true feare of God. Secondly, what wee are to feare in God. Thirdly, by what meanes wee may attaine to this feare.</p>
               <p>There is a two-fold feare; the one is holy and good, called filial or childiſh; the other is bad and naught, termed ſeruile or ſlauiſh: the filiall or childiſh feare is ſuch an one, as is in children towards their parents, who doe reuerence and feare them, as being vnwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to offend them any way, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by words or deeds, through the tender loue and affection, which they doe beare towards them: the ſeruile feare is ſuch an one as is in bondſlaues towards their maiſters, who doe reuerence and feare them, through the dread and feare of puniſhment, which
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:7856:11"/> otherwiſe they are ſure to haue, if they offend and doe contrary to their duties: ſo that ſome do feare him through loue, and care to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend him; and others do feare him through dread of puniſhment, and power to torment them; and it may be defined thus.<note place="margin">What the feare of God is.</note> 
                  <hi>It is a reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Gods maieſtie in our hearts, whereby wee are made vnwilling to offend him in any thing, and moſt willing to pleaſe him in all things, through the loue, which wee beare to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him.</hi> This is a vertue moſt neceſſary and requiſite for all Chriſtians whatſoeuer, as might at large be ſhewed: but let the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>Abraham</hi> ſuffice,<note place="margin">Gen. 20.11.</note> who thinking that the feare of God was not in <hi>Gerar,</hi> vtterly deſpay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of any other vertue, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mooued his wife to ſay that ſhe was his ſiſter: in this reſpect
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:7856:12"/> the feare of God is both by <hi>Dauid</hi> and alſo by <hi>Salomon</hi> called the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of wiſedome;<note place="margin">Pſa. 111.10 Prou. 1.7.</note> that is, the root and fountain of all goodnes, and therefore we muſt feare the Lord,<note place="margin">Deut. 6.13.</note> &amp; ſtand in great awe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence of him. <hi>Thou ſhalt feare</hi> (ſaith <hi>Moſes</hi> to Iſrael) <hi>the Lord thy God, and ſerue him, and ſhalt ſweare by his name. Eſay</hi> doth require the ſame,<note place="margin">Eſay. 8.13.</note> when hee ſaith vnto them; <hi>Sanctifie the Lord of hoaſts, and let him be your feare, and let him be your dread.</hi> But <hi>Salomon</hi> ſayes; <hi>Let vs heare the end of all,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccle. 12.23</note> 
                  <hi>feare God and keepe his commandements,</hi> for this is the whole duty of man.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Theſe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſhould be motiues to vs to fear the Lord.</note>And there are diuers reaſons to mooue vs hereunto; as firſt, the greatnes of his power and might aboue vs. Secondly, his authority and iuriſdiction which he hath o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vs. Thirdly, his goodneſſe and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:7856:12"/> mercy, which hee doth ſhew vnto vs. Fourthly, his maieſty &amp; glory; which doth ſhine &amp; gliſter round about vs. Fifthly, his purity and holineſſe, that is in his eyes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding vs. And laſtly, the great bleſſings which the feare it ſelfe being had will bring vnto vs, for al theſe things may iuſtly worke a feare in men. Meane men do feare great men, and they dare not in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny caſe diſpleaſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> feare their parents, &amp; ſuch as haue a ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling tuition ouer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Workemen feare their maſters by whom they liue &amp; are maintained. Simple per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons feare great ſtates, and ſuch as excell in glory and maieſtie aboue themſelues, though otherwiſe they owe no homage or ſubiectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto them. Looſe liuers and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons feare graue and religious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and ſuch as are zealous for Gods glory and earneſt for the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:7856:13"/> ſaluation of mans ſoule, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſhamed to poure out their euill words, or to commit their wicked facts before them and in their preſence. Laſtly, euery one by nature is forward to apply him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to thoſe things, which hee doth know will bring great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit and benefit vnto himſelfe, and to liue in happineſſe and proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie all the dayes of his life.</p>
               <p>Now to apply this to God and to our ſelues. Firſt, he is of power, and he is able to pay vs home if we do diſpleaſe him: this our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour tels vs when hee biddeth vs <hi>not to feare men who can kill but the body,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 10.28.</note> 
                  <hi>but to feare the Lord who is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to deſtroy both body and ſoule in hell.</hi> Secondly, he hath authoritie and iuriſdiction ouer vs, wee are his, he hath made vs, and he may doe with vs what hee will, as the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:7856:13"/> Potter doth with his veſſell: this reaſon the Lord himſelfe doth giue when he ſaith, <hi>A ſonne honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth his father,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mal. 1.6.</note> 
                  <hi>and a ſeruant his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, if then I bee a father, where is mine honour; and if I bee a maſter where is my feare, ſaith the Lord of hoſts vnto you O Prieſts, that deſpiſe my name.</hi> Thirdly, he is good and kind to vs, his benefits which wee do enioy from him are infinite, we haue all that wee haue from him, euen our liues and all the reſt:<note place="margin">Pſal. 130.4.</note> this reaſon <hi>Dauid</hi> doth touch when he ſaith vnto the Lord, <hi>but mercy is with thee, that thou mareſt be fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</hi> Fourthly, he is a God of infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite maieſtie and glory, and wee are but poore ſimple creatures made of the duſt and clay of the ground; the heauen of heauens cannot containe him, neither can the Angels themſelues ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:7856:14"/> him for his brightnes, vnleſſe they couer their faces with two of their wings: this reaſon doth <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> glance at when hee ſhewes the end wherefore the Lord did pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh his law,<note place="margin">Exo. 22.20.</note> in that glorious and maieſticall manner as hee did, in thunders and lightnings, and the like, ſaying; <hi>For God is come to proue you, and that his feare may be before you, that ye ſinne not.</hi> Fifthly, he is holy and righteous, his eyes are pure eyes, and cannot behold ſin and iniquity; this reaſon is layde downe before the eyes of the Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites, oftentimes in the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, by the ſpirit of God, when hee would draw them to the true feare and ſeruice of God, from all ſuch manners as were found a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Gentiles. Finally, the the commodities, which the feare of the Lord being had, will bring
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:7856:14"/> vnto vs, are exceeding great. For firſt,<note place="margin">The bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits which we ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue ſhould moue vs to feare the Lord.</note> it wil make vs holy and frame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able vnto Gods will, in auoyding thoſe things which hee hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, and performing thoſe things which hee hath comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; <hi>The feare of the Lord</hi> (ſaith <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon) is to hate euill,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prou. 8.13.</note> 
                  <hi>as pride and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogancy &amp; the euill way,</hi> where hee ſheweth that in what meaſure any one feares God, in the ſame mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure he doth loath and deteſt all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, for he ſaith not, to hate euill, as murther and adultery, but pride and arrogancy which lie in the heart, and doe not ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to the world: Yet hee that feareth God will hate them. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, it will make vs bleſſed and happy in all our wayes; <hi>Bleſſed</hi> (ſaith <hi>Dauid) is euery one that feareth the Lord, and walketh in his wayes:</hi> this reaſon the ſweet ſinger of Iſrael, hath alledged,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:7856:15"/> when he ſaith, <hi>feare the Lord, ye his Saints, for nothing wanteth to them that feare him;</hi> nothing he meanes which is good and wholeſome for them,<note place="margin">Pſal. 84.11.</note> as he ſpeakes elſe where, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; <hi>the Lord will giue grace and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and no good thing will hee with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold from them that walke vprightly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, this ſerueth to condemne thoſe that haue not the true feare of the Lord before their eyes. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las their caſe is miſerable, for they ſerue not the true and liuing God, what ſhew of religion ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they do make, or what brags ſoeuer they doe giue foorth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſame: for ſeeing the feare of God is the very beginning of wiſedome, and the foundation or groundſill of Gods worſhippe (as hath bene proued) it is vnpoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, that either they ſhould haue any true wiſedome in them, or elſe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:7856:15"/> religiouſly ſhould ſerue the Lord, when they want this feare, the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cauſe and fountaine thereof.</p>
               <p>Secondly, this may ſerue for to ſtirre vs vp to get the true feare of the Lord vnto our ſelues, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour by all meanes poſſible to bring our hearts thereunto,<note place="margin">Ioh. 4.18.</note> that ſo we may truely ſay of our ſelues, that <hi>the Lord is our dread.</hi> But a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this it may bee obiected, that <hi>perfect loue doth caſt out feare;</hi> and we are commanded to ſerue God without feare.<note place="margin">Luke 1.74.</note> To this I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that perfect loue doth caſt out helliſh and ſlauiſh or ſeruile feare, whereof wee ſpake before, that makes men to tremble before God for feare of puniſhment: but on the contrary ſide, it cauſeth that holy and childiſh feare that makes man carefull to come vnto him, and to worſhip him as wee
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:7856:16"/> ought to doe. From the former of theſe wee are deliuered, but not from the latter. <hi>We haue not receiued the ſpirit of bondage to feare againe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 8.5.</note> 
                  <hi>but the ſpirit of adoption, whereby we cry Abbah Father.</hi> So that true loue is ſo farre off from caſting out this holy feare of adoption, whereby wee are drawne to hate ſinne in loue towards God, and not for puniſhments ſake, that it doth bring it in, and eſtabliſh it within vs; yet this is to bee noted by the way, that ſeruile feare is a good meanes at the firſt to bring vs vnto God, for it prepareth a place for the holy Ghoſt to bring him into our ſoules, as the briſtles bringeth in the thred. But when it is once entred into vs, and hath taken vp the poſſeſſion of our ſoules within vs, then this feare is gone, as the briſtle is when the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:7856:16"/> thred is entred into the hole. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides this we muſt marke, that as the children of God are not by and by perfect; ſo a peece of this feare may ſtill remaine in them, but the feare that is here required, of vs, and which is to laſt for euer, is that feare of reuerence, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we beholding our owne weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and the excellency of God, and his incomprehenſible Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, dare not lift vp our ſelues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, but do ſtand in awe of him with all reuerence, being loath to offend him in any thing, and moſt carefull to pleaſe him in all things; it is ſuch a feare as is in louing children toward their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, in dutifull wiues towards their huſbands, and in faithfull ſubiects towards their Princes, the fountaine whereof is loue, and a due conſideration of his excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:7856:17"/> euery away about vs.<note place="margin">A plain dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the true filiall and ſonne-like feare, &amp; the ſeruile &amp; ſlauiſh feare.</note> Here we may ſee a plaine difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the true filial feare of God and the ſeruile and ſlauiſh feare: the filiall feare keepeth vs from fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall falling away, but the ſeruile doth not; the filiall is onely in the godly, the ſeruile in the wicked; the filiall is a peculiar gift of the ſpirit, ſo is not the ſeruile; and the filial feare is ioyned with loue, but there is no ſeruile feare in loue.</p>
               <p>And as the true feare of God proceeds from loue, ſo it muſt bee continued in loue &amp; end in loue: therefore if the Lord loue thee, then thou doeſt loue him againe; this Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> doth confirme, <hi>We loue him becauſe he loued vs firſt:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 4.19.</note> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine then what loue thou bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt towards God, try whether it be ſound; for certainely if thou loueſt him, thou art beloued of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:7856:17"/> him. It is thought to be a commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thing, and eaſie to loue the Lord,<note place="margin">This feare of God muſt be louely, for where God is not truly loued hee cannot be truly fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</note> and he is a wretch and vnworthy to liue that doth not loue his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker: but let euery one beware leſt it be found in himſelfe, for it is not ſo common a thing to loue the Lord as the world takes it to bee. Bee thou therefore of a good ground, try thy loue by the fruits and effects; therefore if thou loueſt God truely,<note place="margin">Mat. 10.37. Pſal. 63.3. Phil. 3.4.</note> thou doeſt eſteeme him &amp; his fauour aboue all things in the world beſides, counting his louing kindneſſe better vnto thee then life, and the ſignes of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour thy greateſt ioy, all things ſhall be counted but as droſſe and dung in compariſon of it.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, if thou loueſt God, thou wilt then delight in his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence; for the nature of true loue is ſuch, that it earneſtly deſireth the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:7856:18"/> preſence of the party which is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued:<note place="margin">Pſal. 26.8.</note> thou wilt loue his houſe, and the place where his honour dwelleth, thou wilt haue frequent recourſe to thoſe means, by which the Lord is pleaſed to conuerſe with his children, whether pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, as to the hearing of the word; or priuate, as reading, ſinging, &amp;c. Take all occaſions to ſpeake vnto him by prayer and meditation:<note place="margin">Phil. 1.25.</note> yea thou wilt haue an ardent deſire to be diſſolued, that thou mayeſt bee with Chriſt, and to be abſent from the body,<note place="margin">2, Cor. 5.8.</note> that thou mighteſt bee preſent with the Lord.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Readineſſe to obey, ſignes of true loue.</note>Fourthly, our loue to God may be tryed by our readines in obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his commands. Loue can hardly deny any worke which the party beloued doth enioyne. Loth we are to deny to doe any thing for thoſe whom we entirely loue.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:7856:18"/> 
                  <hi>Hee that hath my commandements and keepeth them,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 14.21</note> 
                  <hi>he it is that loueth me,</hi> ſaith our Sauiour: <hi>this is the loue of God, that wee keepe his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, &amp; his commandements are not greeuous.</hi> So then,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 5.3.</note> where there is loue, there is obedience, yea willing &amp; carefull obedience. This may ſerue for the great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of all ſuch, as haue Gods loue manifeſted vnto them, for as the terrors are great, which that man hath in his conſcience, who is in doubt of the loue of the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty towards him: ſo is the comfort as great which that man hath, who is hereof perſwaded, for <hi>come tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation, or diſtreſſe, or perſecution,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 8 25, 11. Heb. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>or famine, or nakedneſſe, or perill, or ſword, or life, or death,</hi> yet the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of Gods loue will ſupport him: this aſſurance doth make bitter things ſweet, and gall to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:7856:19"/> as hony. Comfort then thy heart thou beloued of the Lord, let nothing diſmay thee, though the wicked mocke, though the world ſcorne thee, though thy acquaintance hate thee, yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member God loues and fauours thee,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 1.8.</note> and hath manifeſted the ſame vnto thee. <hi>Is not my loue better vnto thee then ten children,</hi> ſaid <hi>Elkanah,</hi> to <hi>Hannah?</hi> ſo is not the loue of God vnto vs better then tenne worlds: let then the meditation of this harden thy face like braſſe againſt all dangers and ſad times of temptations and perſecution, for God ſhall giue his beloued reſt, they ſhall be deliuered, for he will helpe them with his right hand.</p>
               <p>Therfore to this feare we muſt ſtir vp our ſoules euery day, and ſo farre as we would either worſhip
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:7856:19"/> God aright, or haue his bleſſings powred downe vpon vs; whether for this life, or the life to come, we muſt ſtriue and contend with our ſoules and our hearts to bring them hereunto: that ſo wee may alwayes reuerence and dread the great name of the Lord of hoſts: doubtleſſe we ſhall neuer ſerue the Lord aright, or become happy and bleſſed vntill this bee brought to paſſe: well wee may performe ſome duties in outward appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, wee ſhall neuer looke to all with a good heart and conſcience within. And howſoeuer we proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and flouriſh for a while, yet woe and deſtruction will ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take vs at the laſt; but let his feare bee once planted within vs, then ſhall wee inwardly and from the heart, haue a reſpect vnto all his commandements, and bee moſt
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:7856:20"/> carefull to pleaſe him in all things, and then againe ſhall wee proſper and flouriſh for euer, not onely in this world, but much more in the world to come. If any then ſhall come vnto vs, to entice vs vnto a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wickedneſſe whatſoeuer, as <hi>Potiphars</hi> wife came vnto <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 39.8.</note> and enticed him vnto vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleaneneſſe, wee ſhall not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent vnto him therein, no more then hee did vnto her, who was kept therefrom by the feare of the Lord.</p>
               <p>This ſhould teach euery one of vs dayly to thinke of and bee fully perſwaded of the glorious and continuall preſence of Almighty God.<note place="margin">The pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God euer looking vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs, ſhould be a meanes to keepe vs from ſinne.</note> That whereſoeuer we are, &amp; and whatſoeuer we thinke, ſpeake, or do, God vnderſtands it, knowes it, &amp; beholds it, our thoughts, our words.<note place="margin">Pſal. 139.4.</note> 
                  <hi>There is not a word in my
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:7856:20"/> tongue, but thou O Lord knoweſt it altogether:</hi> our deeds in publike, &amp; ſecret,<note place="margin">Prou. 15.3.</note> 
                  <hi>the eye of the Lord is in euery place, beholding both the euill and the good.</hi> This conſideration and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, wee ought all to labour for it being a notable meanes to worke true feare in our hearts: therefore let vs eſteeme of euery place as <hi>Iacob</hi> did of <hi>Bethel,</hi> what hee then ſayde vrge ſtill vpon thy ſoule, <hi>The Lord is preſent, and I was not aware of it.</hi> Let thy ſhop bee a <hi>Bethel,</hi> thy chamber a <hi>Bethel,</hi> thy cloſet a <hi>Bethel,</hi> for God is there preſent. Oh that this meditation did take place in our hearts, how many ſinnes would it keepe vs from? how conſcionably ſhould wee walke? how vpright would be. The chiefe ſountaine of all hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie is either ignorance, or not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidering of this diuine property
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:7856:21"/> of God; and ſurely if any thing will baniſh hypocriſie, this will do it. A <hi>man cannot chuſe but be good</hi> (ſayth <hi>Boetius) who ſtill remembers, that he ſtands in the preſence of the Lord.</hi> Let this meditation then be euer in our mind, that God is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vs and behind vs, within thee and without thee, on thy right hand and on thy left hand, alwaies neere and neuer farre off; and ſo ſhalt thou walke vprightly.</p>
               <p>Holy <hi>Iob,</hi> we ſee, tooke that courſe that the Lord would haue vs take for the repreſſing of all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate luſt and affections: <hi>I made</hi> ſayth he,<note place="margin">Iob. 31.1.</note> 
                  <hi>a couenant with my eyes, why then ſhould I thinke on a mayde.</hi> A carnal man would haue thought this too much curioſity and nice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, what not to looke on the beauty and comely viſage of a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, at leaſt, not to take ſome li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:7856:21"/> for thoughts tending that way, it is too too much preciſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, who can take any notice of ſuch things in vs?<note place="margin">Verſ. 2.</note> Oh (ſayth <hi>Iob) what portion ſhould I haue of God from aboue, and what inheritance from the almighty from on high.</hi> I durſt not giue any way vnto the fleſh in any ſort, for that were the directeſt courſe to depriue my ſelfe of the comforts of the word and ſpirit here, and of the crowne of happineſſe, which is reſerued for the Saints in the world to come. Albeit I ſhould ſpeede litle the worſe with men, yet I ſhould bee ſure to come ſhort of many ſpeciall fauours and bleſſings of the Lord: and further he addeth, <hi>Is not deſtruction to the wicked, and ſtrange puniſhments to the workers of iniquitie.</hi> Suppoſe I ſhould e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape the cenſures of men, yet
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:7856:22"/> hath not the Lord meanes that I cannot conceiue of, for the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of rebellious ſinners, and though things may be ſmothered for a time, cannot he bring ſecret ſins to open ſhame: grant that it be kept cloſe from the eyes of the world, yet doth not he behold my wayes, and tels al my ſteps; though the eyes of men take the view one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the outward actions, yet hee looketh vpon the inward diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, and affection of the heart. Theſe and the like reaſons he vſed to keepe himſelfe in order, and fright his conſcience from all manner of ſinne and impietie, as is more fully deſcribed vnto vs in that chapter.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, this may ſerue for terror to all ſuch as liue in ſinne; what greater terror to a theefe, then to haue the iudge
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:7856:22"/> an eye witneſſe of his vilany.<note place="margin">Let all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblers take notice of this.</note> So what greater terror to the wicked then this, to haue the Lord behold their doings. Come then and learne thou diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling hypocrite, thou that cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt and dallyeſt with the Lord, God hath ſpyed and doth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpy thy rottenneſſe within, for all thy painted outſide. Hee knoweth that though thou wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt Chriſts liuery on thy backe thou weareſt the diuels fauour in thy boſome. Thinke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this you lurking diuels, cloſe enemies of the Church whoſe ſleepe departs from you till you haue cauſed ſome to fall: the Lord ſeeth your plots and cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning deuiſes, your cloſe pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes againſt his Church and people, <hi>But hee that ſitteth in Heauen ſhall laugh you to ſcorne,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 2.</note>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:7856:23"/> 
                  <hi>the Lord ſhall haue you in deriſion.</hi> Take notice of this all you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterers and whoremongers, who ſay in your hearts; <hi>Who ſees vs, wee are compaſſed about with darkeneſſe, we need not feare.</hi> Behold the Lord himſelfe ſeeth thy villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and looketh thee in the face, in the act of doing. Let vs all conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this and bee better aduiſed, thinke not by denying, excuſing, colouring, or cloaking them to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyde the ſhame, for what if men do count you innocent, yet God will bring in euidence to finde you guilty, and therefore he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe will witneſſe againſt thee,<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.</note> and ſet thy ſinnes order before thee.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, this may ſerue to ſtirre vs vp, and encourage vs to well doing. What lazie ſeruant will not put foorth his ſtrength when his maiſters eye is on him? So, who
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:7856:23"/> is it, were he well perſwaded that the Lord is a ſpectator and behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of his doings, would not put foorth his ſtrength to the Lords worke. Were this well conſidered how couragious ſhould wee bee, both in the duties of our generall and ſpeciall callings;<note place="margin">Seeing the Lord is the beholder of all our acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and wil reward the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> let this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame vs to practiſe pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, &amp; cauſe vs to make euen holy thoughs precious.</note> how forward would we be to euery good work. Be not then ſlothfull in Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, ſtand not all day idle, be euer doing of good. Not the leaſt good can be done, but he doth know it, be it done neuer ſo ſecretly, yet he ſeeth it: hee ſeeth thy prayers, hee heareth thy grones, hee bottles vp thy teares which are ſhed at mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night, and will reward them. Thou needſt not looke for witneſſe, to take notice of thy actions, God himſelfe is witneſſe, and thy owne conſcience alſo: thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is as a thouſand witneſſes,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:7856:24"/> and God as a thouſand conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: how many witneſſes wouldſt thou haue? canſt thou deſire more? Let this enflame vs to pietie, and cauſe vs to make eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> holy thoghts pretious: for, as there is not the leaſt euill in the heart which can eſcape Gods knowledge; no more is there the leaſt good mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and cogitation. Oh that this were well weighed, then would not there bee ſo many lazie Chriſtians, as now there bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs. Let it bee conſidered, and let his knowledge ſupport thee in euery good action.</p>
               <p>And that we may the better at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to theſe graces let vs vſe fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent prayer vnto almighie God, and that dayly, humbly beſeech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him of his infinite goodneſſe and mercy, to beget and worke this holy feare in our hearts. <hi>I will
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:7856:24"/> put my feare in their hearts,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ier. 32.39.40.</note> 
                  <hi>that they ſhall not depart from me.</hi> Heere we ſee it is a propper gift,<note place="margin">It is muſike to God to heare Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.</note> and worke of God himſelfe, and we muſt not thinke to haue it, vnleſſe we vſe the meanes of Prayer, which God hath ordained to obtaine his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings and graces, as Saint <hi>Iames</hi> ſpeaketh: <hi>Wee haue not,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iam. 4.2.</note> 
                  <hi>becauſe wee aske not.</hi> Therefore ſaith <hi>Dauid: Vnite my heart vnto thee,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 86.11.</note> 
                  <hi>that</hi> I <hi>may feare thy name:</hi> And God is ſo well pleaſed with our Prayers, when they come vnto him, that there is no melodious harmony ſo pleaſant in our eares, as a Prayer proceeding from an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and broken heart, is in the eares of the Lord of Hoſts: let vs preſent our petitions with our ſoules full of griefe, and our eyes full of teares vnto men, and wee ſhall bee tedious and troubleſome
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:7856:25"/> vnto them for the moſt part, as the woman of <hi>Canaan</hi> was vnto the diſciples. <hi>Send her away,</hi> ſay they to our Sauiour,<note place="margin">Math. 15.13</note> 
                  <hi>for ſhe cryeth after vs.</hi> But Chriſt hath no greater ioy then to heare and releiue ſuch worthy beleeuers as ſhe was. Now ſith it is a thing ſo well pleaſing vnto him, he cannot but grant and ſatisfie the deſires of ſuch as faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and feruently call vpon him.</p>
               <p>Therefore ſeeing the Lord is ſo pleaſed with penitent ſinners whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they come vnto him,<note place="margin">The true penitent ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner feareth to diſpleaſe God by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting the leaſt ſinne.</note> let euery one of vs labour for true and ſound re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, to bee humbled in the ſight and knowledge of our ſinnes with godly ſorrow, which may continually bring foorth in vs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance to ſaluation, neuer to be repented of,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 7.11</note> and this will bring foorth feare. <hi>Behold this godly ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, what feare it hath wrought in
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:7856:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> you.</hi> The penitent ſinner feareth to diſpleaſe God,<note place="margin">This feare of God muſt be durable not onely for a time, but it muſt bee to the end of our dayes.</note> to diſobey his word or to do any thing which he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth will not bee well pleaſing in Gods ſight, and ſo out of his true loue vnto God, is afrayde leſt by committing the leaſt ſinne, hee ſhould procure the anger of God againſt him, and this our repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance muſt continue all the dayes of our life, according to <hi>Dauids</hi> ſaying: <hi>The feare of the Lord which bringeth repentance endureth for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer.</hi> And great reaſon it ſhould be ſo, for wee are commanded to bee conſtant, and to perſeuer in god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines euen to the end: but this can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be vnleſſe the feare of God be in vs alwayes, therefore ſaith God, <hi>I will put my feare in their hearts that they ſhall not depart from mee.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ier. 32.40.</note> And it is the ſpeciall commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, that we ſhould feare
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:7856:26"/> the Lord our God for our good alwayes, in our youth, middle-age, and old age, euen vnto our death, and not poſt it off till old-age, as a number doe, ſpending all their time in ryot, and all manner of prophaneneſſe: it is long ere they beginne, yet at length they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>think themſelues, and ſo are afraid to ſinne as they haue done; but a number of ſuch neuer leaue ſinne, till ſinne leaues them, whoſe ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes are pittifull and lamentable. It is true which is ſaid, better late then neuer,<note place="margin">Pſal. 72.5.</note> ſo it is as true, that large teares, and late repentance is not alwayes true. <hi>Dauid</hi> deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing the time,<note place="margin">Pal. 119.8.</note> ſaith, <hi>They ſhall feare thee, as long as the Sunne and Moone endures throughout al generations:</hi> let vs therfore continually vſe al good meanes to keepe vs in this feare, that all of vs ioyntly, and each one
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:7856:26"/> in particular may truly ſay with <hi>Dauid, O Lord I am deuoted to thy feare.</hi> Seuenthly,<note place="margin">Let vs not be diſcoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, though our repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance be but in a begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, yet if it be true, God will meete it with mercy. Rom. 7.19.</note> here is great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to al weak Chriſtians, who are much diſcouraged with their weak proceedings in grace: they feele not their hearts ſo broken as they deſire. They deſire with all their hearts to turne vnto the Lord, to leaue ſin, but ſtill they fall, and that foulely. The good they would do they do not; the euill they would not do, that do they dayly: well, is it thus? yet bee thou not diſcoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged: for though thy repentance be but in a beginning, yet if it bee true, God will meete it with mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. Thou ſayeſt thou deſireſt: Is thy deſire true and vnfained?<note place="margin">2. Cor. 8.12</note> Doeſt thou deſire to walke, ſo as that God may be glorified? Doeſt thou expreſſe thy deſires by vſing of all good meanes? And is not thy
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:7856:27"/> deſire idle? and art thou content to doe any labour, &amp; take any paines for the obtaining of grace? doeſt thou thirſt after it as the Hart doth after the riuers of waters? If it be thus, aſſure thy ſelfe thy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſire is highly pleaſing vnto God and moſt acceptable vnto him, the Lord he will not reiect it, nor thee in regard of it, hee will not breake the bruiſed reed, nor quench the ſmoking flaxe.<note place="margin">Mat. 12.20</note> Till he bring forth iudgement vnto victory, hee doth not contemne the leaſt meaſure of his owne grace he hath beſtowed on thee, be it neuer ſo ſmal a quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie if true, it is his owne guift, &amp; <hi>his gifts are without repentance,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 11.29</note> hee cannot deſpiſe that which himſelf hath giuen, neither take that away for euer which hee hath once be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed: thy creeping is acceptable to God, goe on with comfort
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:7856:27"/> conſtantly vnto the end.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, here the Prophet ſaith,<note place="margin">Prou. 3.7. Let all men therfore ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine their owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, whether they haue left their ſins if they haue, they may ſafely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude they are ſuch as feare God.</note> 
                  <hi>Bleſſed is the man that feareth the Lord: &amp; Salomon</hi> he ſaith, <hi>Feare the Lord and depart from euill;</hi> for no man can depart from euill vnleſſe he feare God, ſo none feares God truely but he doth ceaſe from ſin, therefore they that boaſt of their feare, and yet liue in their former ſinnes, are lyers againſt the truth, and deceiue their owne ſoules. Let all men therefore ſeriouſly examin their owne conſcience, whether they haue left their ſinnes, and are become new creatures in Chriſt Ieſus, and whether they haue a full purpoſe and reſolution of heart for time to come, to hate that which is euill: if they haue, they may conclude to their euerlaſting ioy and comfort, that they are ſuch as feare God; if not, then let them
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:7856:28"/> know, they cannot approoue vnto their owne ſoules that they haue this feare, for he that continueth in the practiſe of ſinne, without any penitency, hath not the true feare of God.<note place="margin">Pſal. 36.1.</note> 
                  <hi>The wicked haue no feare of God before their eyes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Let vs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore keepe Gods Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts and not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly talke of them, but practiſe them and doe them.</note>Firſt, this teaches vs to walke in the path of Gods Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, &amp; not to talke of them on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or to commend them, but to practiſe them and doe them: the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> therefore, ſheweth plainely who they are that feares God; ſaying, <hi>The mercy of the Lord is from euerlaſting to euerlaſting,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſa. 10<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.17 18. Pſa. 128.1. Pſa. 119 63. Deut. 8.6.</note> 
                  <hi>vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them that feares him, to ſuch as keepe his Couenant, and remember his Commandements to doe them, and bleſſed is euery one that feareth the Lord, and walketh in his wayes,</hi> and <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith, <hi>I am a companion of all them that feare thee, and keepe thy
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:7856:28"/> Commandements.</hi> This muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore teach euery one carefully to obſerue and keep Gods Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, according to the ſaying of God by <hi>Moſes: Thou ſhalt keepe the Commandement of the Lord thy God, to walke in his wayes, and to feare him.</hi> In vaine therefore doe they boaſt of their feare, ſeruice, &amp; worſhip of God, who inſtead of keeping Gods Comandements, break them all, &amp; delight the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues in nothing more, then in commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of ſin, &amp; tranſgreſſing the Law of God, let vs therfore take <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> counſell;<note place="margin">Eccle. 12.13 In all Gods children in whom the true feare of God is, there muſt be vpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and ſincerity of heart.</note> 
                  <hi>Feare God and keepe his Commandements, for this is the whole duty of man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, wee muſt get vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſſe of heart in the whole courſe of Gods worſhip and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice. Hee that walketh in his vprightnes, feareth the Lord. <hi>Iob</hi>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:7856:29"/> was an vpright man, and one that feared God. <hi>Cornelius</hi> was a iuſt man, and one that feared God, with all his houſe:<note place="margin">Pro. 14.2. Iob. 1. Act. 10.22. Verſe 2.</note> and certainely in all Gods people in whom the true feare of God is, there cannot but be vprightneſſe of heart voyde of all hypocriſie, and a true endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to approoue their hearts vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, to bee true and ſound in all things, as knowing, that God knoweth and beholdeth all, and he who will iudge them all at the latter day.<note place="margin">To goe on conſtantly in grace vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the end, is a true ſigne of the holy feare of God. Ier. 32.40. Pro. 24.24.</note> Therefore let vs all get vprightneſſe of heart, and goe on conſtantly in the grace and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of God, cleaning ſo faſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, as neuer to fall away from him, for thoſe that haue made ſome good beginnings, and yet afterwards fall away from him, do euidently declare, that they neuer had this true feare of God, for
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:7856:29"/> God doth ſo put his feare in the hearts of his Children, that they ſhall neuer depart from him: they may ſometimes fall through infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, but as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, They riſe vp againe, therefore they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not finally fall away from God, none can plucke him out of his hands: Satan cannot,<note place="margin">Ioh. 10.29.</note> becauſe he that is in vs,<note place="margin">Iohn. 4.4.</note> is ſtronger then hee that is in the world: Sinne can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, becauſe grace will preuaile a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it: The world cannot,<note place="margin">1. Iohn 5.4.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>this is our victory, whereby we ouercome the world, euen our Faith.</hi> And the Apoſtle concludeth ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally for all other matters, that <hi>Neither death, nor life, nor Angels,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 8.38, 39.</note> 
                  <hi>nor Principalities, nor Powers, nor things preſent, nor things to come, nor height, nor depth, nor any other creature, ſhall be able to ſeparate vs from the loue of God, which is in Chriſt
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:7856:30"/> Ieſus our Lord.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of this grace, ſhuld be a ſpeciall motiue to vs to feare the Lord.</note> And to ſtirre vs vp to the performance of this duety, whereby we may get the true feare of the Lord, let vs remember the excellency of this grace, and how it maketh all thoſe in whom it is to be moſt excellent.<note place="margin">Mal. 3.16.</note> For, <hi>a booke of remembrance is written before God, for them that feare the Lord, and they ſhall be mine, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 31.30.</note> 
                  <hi>in that day when</hi> I <hi>make vp my Iewels.</hi> Here we ſee, God hath them in euerlaſting remembrance, neuer to forget them, as being his Iewels and chiefeſt treaſure. The woman that excelleth all, is ſhee that feareth the Lord;<note place="margin">Pro. 15.16. Pſal. 37.16.</note> this <hi>Salomon</hi> deſcribes the excellency of this feare, aboue all other things: <hi>Bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is a little with the feare of the Lord, then great Treaſure, and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble therewith.</hi> A little that a righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous man hath is better then the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:7856:30"/> riches of many wicked men, and of all people.<note place="margin">Pſa. 147.11</note> 
                  <hi>The Lord ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth pleaſure in them that feare him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, we learne from hence that this bleſſed man that fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the Lord,<note place="margin">No good thing will the Lord withhold from them that feare him.</note> hath the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of temporall bleſſings, as riches, honour, preferment, length of dayes, bleſſing vpon our labours, and all that wee haue. Doeſt thou then deſire riches? Wouldeſt thou come to honour? Wouldeſt thou liue long, and ſee good dayes? Then bee carefull to feare the Lord, and bee thou ſure thou ſhalt haue theſe bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, or at leaſt, as good in ſtead of them.<note place="margin">Pro. 22.4. Pro. 10.27. Pr. 9.10.11. Pſal. 128.</note> 
                  <hi>By the feare of the Lord are riches, honour, and life, the feare of the Lord prolongeth dayes, and by it thy dayes ſhall bee multiplyed
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:7856:31"/> and the yeeres of thy life ſhall bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed. Bleſſed is euery one that feareth the Lord, for thou ſhalt eate the the labour of thine hands: happy ſhalt thou be, and it ſhall be well with thee: Loe thus ſhall the man bee bleſſed that feareth the Lord.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, wouldeſt thou haue God to deliuer thee and ſaue thee from trouble? then feare the Lord. <hi>For the Angel of the Lord encampeth round about them that feare him,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 34.7.</note> 
                  <hi>and deliuereth them.</hi> Wouldeſt thou haue plenty, or at leaſt a compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent liuing, to enioy Gods good bleſſings? then feare God, for their is no want to them that feare him. <hi>The Lyons doe lurke and ſuffer hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 9.9.10</note> 
                  <hi>but they that feare God ſhall want to manner of thing that is good.</hi> Wouldeſt thou haue thy hearts deſire granted thee of God, ſo far forth as ſhal be agreeable to his
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:7856:31"/> will?<note place="margin">Pſal. 37.4.</note> 
                  <hi>Then delight thy ſelfe in the Lord, and hee ſhall giue thee thine hearts deſire: yea, he will fulfill the deſires of them that feare him, hee will heare their cry, and will helpe them.</hi> Wouldeſt thou haue all things to be well with thee? then feare the Lord, for he taketh plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in them that feare him.<note place="margin">Pſal. 147 11. Eccle. 8.12.</note> 
                  <hi>And though a ſinner doth euill an hundred times, and his dayes be prolonged, yet ſurely I know that it ſhall bee well with them that feare God, which feare before him.</hi> And though ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny troubles, and manifold miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes are in the world, &amp; though the righteous fall into manifold afflictions. Yet as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Eccle. 7.18.</note> 
                  <hi>He that feareth God, ſhall come forth of them all,</hi> ſo that it will make vs bleſſed &amp; happy in all our waies, ſo that the feare of the Lord brings with it alwaies a plenty of al good
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:7856:32"/> things, and comes laden with the bleſſings of God, whereſoeuer it comes: for all theſe cauſes now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſed, ſhould we feare the Lord, and endeauor to pleaſe him.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The feare of the Lord giueth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding to the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</note>Fourthly, hee that feareth the Lord, hath the promiſe of ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all graces, as knowledge, inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, wiſedome, and the like. Art thou ignorant in Gods matters, and wouldeſt faine know and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the wayes of God? then feare the Lord. <hi>For what man is he that feareth the Lord, him ſhall hee teach in the way that hee ſhall chooſe:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 25.12. Verfe 14.</note> yea, <hi>the ſecret of the Lord is among them that feare him, and he will ſhew them his Couenant, the feare of the Lord is the beginning of wiſedome.</hi> A <hi>good vnderſtanding haue all they that doe thereafter.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal 111.10</note> Wouldeſt thou haue the Lord to ſhew pitty and compaſſion vpon thee, and to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:7856:32"/> thee all thy ſinnes? O then feare the Lord:<note place="margin">Mal. 3.16.17</note> 
                  <hi>For the Lord wil ſpare them that feare him, as a man that ſpareth his owne ſonne that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth him, &amp; as a father pittieth his Children, ſo the Lord pittieth them that feare him:</hi> Yea, <hi>the mercy of the Lord is from euerlaſting to euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting vpon them that feare him, and his righteouſneſſe vpon childrens children:</hi> Againe,<note place="margin">Pſal. 103.13</note> 
                  <hi>the Lord heareth the Prayers of thoſe that feare him, and granteth their requeſt:</hi> Yea, <hi>the Lord will giue grace and glory, and no good thing will hee withhold fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them that walke vprightly.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 84.11.</note> Thus wee ſee no grace needefull to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, ſhall be wanting to vs, if we feare the Lord,</p>
               <p>Laſtly, it hath the maine promiſe of eternall life in the world to come: <hi>His end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe mercy is on them that feare
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:7856:33"/> him from generation to generation.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The maine reaſon to enforce vs to labour for this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly feare is, that it hath the promiſes of eternall life in the world to come. Luke 150. Pſal. 85.9. Mal. 2.5. Pſal. 25.12.</note> This is a main reaſon to enforce vs to labour for this holy feare; and howſoeuer the wicked beleeue it not, but account it altogether in vaine to feare God and ſerue him, yet let no man doubt of it who belongs to God, for as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth: <hi>Surely, Gods ſaluation is nigh all them that feare him.</hi> And the couenant of life and peace was with <hi>Leui,</hi> becauſe he feared God, and the ſoule of him that feareth God ſhall dwell at eaſe:<note place="margin">Deut 5.20.</note> yea, <hi>If we feare the Lord alwayes, it ſhall be well with vs, and with our children for euer.</hi> The conſideration of all which ſhould moue euery one of vs to breake out with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſaying, <hi>Who would not feare thee,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ier. 10.7. Reuel. 15.7, Pſa. 115.13.</note> 
                  <hi>O King of Nations,</hi> and with Gods ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts. <hi>Who wil not feare thee O Lord, and glorifie thy Name, for
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:7856:33"/> thou onely art holy. Loe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Theſe gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes ſhould moue vs to feare the Lord. 2. Cor. 7.1. Phil. 2.12. Eſay 8.13.</note> 
                  <hi>thus will the Lord bleſſe them that feare him,</hi> both ſmall and great. <hi>Therefore ſeeing we haue ſuch promiſes, let vs cleanſe our ſelues from all filthineſſe of the fleſh and ſpirit, perfecting ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe in the feare of God: Worke out your ſaluation with feare and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling: ſanctifie the Lord of Hoſts himſelfe, and let him be your dread. Now let the feare of the Lord be vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you, take heede and doe it.</hi> And whatſoeuer yee doe, doe it in the feare of the Lord faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and with a perfect heart. Let vs with good King <hi>Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaphat,</hi> feare the Lord,<note place="margin">2. Chr. 19.79.</note> and ſet our hearts earneſtly to ſeeke him: <hi>For as the Heauen is high a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the Earth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Chr 20.3 Pſal. 103.11</note> 
                  <hi>ſo great is Gods mercy towards them that feare him, as farre as the Eaſt is from the Weſt, ſo farre hath God ſet our
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:7856:34"/> tranſgreſſions from vs.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 33.8.</note> 
                  <hi>O let all the earth feare the Lord, let all the Inhabitants of the World ſtand in awe of him:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 2.11</note> 
                  <hi>Serue the Lord with feare, and reioyce before him with reuerence.</hi> The Lord of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy giue vs this grace, and good Lord vnite our hearts to thee, that wee may feare thy Name, <hi>For thou onely,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 86.11. Pſal. 76.7.</note> 
                  <hi>O Lord, euen thou art to be feared, and who may ſtand in thy ſight when thou art an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry?</hi> Wherefore let vs performe theſe things with care and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and no doubt but wee ſhall haue the true feare of the Lord within vs, which will bee a comfort vnto vs for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.<note place="margin">Our chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ioy and delight ſhould be in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Now follwes the practiſe of this bleſſed man, and that is in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of piety, <hi>and delights greatly in his Commandements:</hi>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:7856:34"/> that is, the whole Doctrine, diuinely inſpired is the very ioy of his heart, and delight of his ſoule: <hi>It is ſweeter</hi> vnto him, <hi>then the Honny and the Honny-combe: It is more precious</hi> vnto him <hi>then gold; yea, then much fine gold.</hi> It is more worth vnto him then the whole World, and where the heart is once enkindled with loue, there the imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation imbraceth with dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt apprehenſion: the thoughts are impatient of any other obiect: all the powers of the Soule, are vnited in a ſtrong endeauour for the attaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the whole minde muſt needes bee poſſeſt with Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation and Prayer. If hee delight in the Law of the LORD his GOD, hee muſt needes meditate therein,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:7856:35"/> And this feruency of the heart cannot poſſibly be incloſed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the compaſſe of the breſt, it will ſpred it ſelfe in ſpeech and actions as is plaine by <hi>Dauids</hi> ſpeech:<note place="margin">Pſal. 37.30</note> 
                  <hi>The mouth of the righteous will ſpeake of wiſedome, and his tongue will talke of iudgement, for the Law of God is in his heart:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſa. 119.167.</note> and <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith, <hi>My ſoule hath kept thy teſtimonies, for I loue them exceedingly.</hi> And this loue, delight, meditation, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe in the Commandements of God, of this bleſſed man, is not a morning cloud, and as the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning dew, before the Sunne, but like the light of the Sunne, that ſhineth more and more vnto per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect day: it is not for a ſtart, for feare, vpon reſtraint, for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reputation, for aduantage, or to couer the terrors of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence for a while, but it is out of a
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:7856:35"/> free reſolution, and with vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunted conſtancy, as hee ſpeakes elſe where day and night.</p>
               <p>So that Gods Law and Word cannot ſimply profit vs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <note place="margin">Gods word cannot bee profitable, except firſt it be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs.</note> except we take ioy and comfort in the ſame. We muſt firſt taſte and proue the ſweeteneſſe thereof, wee muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hand finde out and feele the vertue thereof. <hi>When wiſedome en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treth into thy heart,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 2.10.11 Pſal. 1.2.</note> 
                  <hi>and knowledge delighteth thy ſoule: then (and not before) ſhall counſell preſerue thee, and vnderſtanding ſhall keepe thee, and deliuer thee from the euill way, and from the man that ſpeaketh fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things, &amp;c.</hi> When we once delight in the law of the Lord, &amp; exerciſe our ſelues therein day and night, then ſhal we floriſh like the planted trees by the riuers of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that are fruitfull in due ſeaſon,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:7856:36"/> whoſe leaues ſhall not fade in any drought of danger; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I ſay, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer we do &amp; take in hand ſhall proſper: ſo that if we delight in the Commandements, we ſhall finde comfort in the miniſtery of the word: for there is true ioy &amp; peace to be found, there is ioy and ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the ſweet promiſes of God, faith, grace, ſpiritual ſtrength, and euery good thing offered vnto vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The church of God ſhould bee our greateſt pleaſure, for there wee ſhall find foode for our ſoules.</note>Gods Church with the holy mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry therof, is Chriſts Garden of pleaſures, wherein he banqueteth with his elect, euen he which is the fountain of the garden (the true &amp; only head of all Churches, the wel of liuing waters, &amp; the Spring of <hi>Lebanon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Can. 4.12.15. &amp; 5.</note> hither he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to eate his pleaſant fruit: this only true &amp; Chriſtian Church being his ſiſter, &amp; Spouſe, is as a garden encloſed, as a ſpring &amp; fountaine ſealed vp:
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:7856:36"/> hither Chriſt commeth to make merry with his friends, and to banquet with his beloued; there hee gathereth his myrrh with his ſpices, there hee eates the hony-combe with his hony, and drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his wine with his milke, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighting himſelfe with the ſweete pleaſant and profitable fruits that the children of God doe yeeld vnto him.<note place="margin">Comfort and loue to Gods word procures li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and ſo by Gods bleſſing faith and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience. Rom. 10.14</note> Now the reaſon why the word of God cannot profite vs without delight, is, becauſe that comfort and liking, prouoke and procure men to bee diligent in hearing, &amp; diligent hearing by Gods bleſſing begets faith, and faith brings vs aſſurance of Gods loue &amp; protection, the euidence and certainety whereof are Gods promiſes which are yea &amp; Amen.<note place="margin">Gal. 5.6. 1. Co. 13.7. Gen. 31.30 40.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Againe, loue ſupporteth our la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and ſetteth our faith a worke:
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:7856:37"/> 
                  <hi>It ſuffereth all things, it beleeueth all things, if endureth all things. Iacob</hi> loued <hi>Rachel,</hi> ſerued twiſe ſeuen yeares for her ſake: neither the heate of the day, nor the froſt of the night, nor the breaking of his ſleepe, no danger, loſſe or croſſe could driue him out. So the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites toyled and trauelled many miles to the temple, hungry, wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and thirſty, they going through the vale of <hi>Baca,</hi> make wells therein, contented to refreſh themſelues with the raine that filled their pooles, in ſo barren a wilderneſſe,<note place="margin">Pſal. 84. &amp;c.</note> and thus they went from ſtrength to ſtrength till they appeared before the Lord their God, in <hi>Sion.</hi> And what was the reaſon hereof that they ſtill pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed without any interruption, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen this was the reaſon, <hi>O Lord of Hoſts, how amiable are thy Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacles,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:7856:37"/> our ſoule longeth and fainteth for thy Courts, our hearts and fleſh reioyce in the liuing God. Bleſſed are they that dwell in thy houſe, and in whoſe hearts are thy wayes.</hi> For the Lord our God is a Sunne and ſhield vs, the authour of all good things, and the deliuerer from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill: hee will giue grace and glory and no good thing will hee with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold from them that are ſincere: therefore <hi>O Lord of hoſts,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The onely way to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit by the word and miniſtry is, to delight in the ſame.</note> 
                  <hi>bleſſed is the man that truſteth in thee.</hi> Here we ſee that euery action without affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is laborious &amp; toyleſome, none euer ſoundly profited by the word, and holy miniſtry thereof, that delighted not in the ſame.</p>
               <p>Firſt, this ſerueth to ſtirre vp our loue and liking of Gods truth, to raiſe vp our dead affections, and to cauſe our dull ſenſes more ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly to embrace the ſame, and
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:7856:38"/> to ſet before our eyes the beſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples for imitation and practiſe:<note place="margin">The word is of power and is able to conuert our ſoules to the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing God.</note> and that we may be perſwaded the better, for the performance of this duty, let vs conſider the ſingular fruites and effectes of Gods word, which wee ought ſo worthily to affect. Gods law and word is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of it ſelfe to conuert our ſoules from ſinne and Sathan, to God and godlineſſe, heauen and happineſſe, his teſtimony is ſure to giue wiſedome to the ſimple. <hi>The ſtatutes of the Lord are right,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 19.7.8 9.20.11.</note> 
                  <hi>and reioyce the heart, the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements of the Lord is pure, and giueth light to the eyes, the feare of the Lord is cleane, the iudgements of the Lord are true and righteous altogether, by them is thy ſeruant made circumſpect, in keeping of them there is great reward,</hi> and therefore <hi>they are more to bee deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:7856:38"/> then gold, yea then much fine gold, ſweeter alſo then hony, and the hony combe.</hi> Gods word is the meanes for young and old to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe their wicked wayes, a counſeller to aduiſe vs, a Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorne to our feete, a light to our pathes, a reſoluer of our doubts, a ſweetning of our affections, able to reuiue vs being dead, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaith <hi>Dauid, I will delight in thy ſtatutes, I will not forget thy word,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.16 72.97. ver. 103.</note> 
                  <hi>the law of thy mouth is better vnto me then thouſands of gold and ſiluer: O how loue I thy law, it is my meditatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> continually, how ſweet are thy promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes vnto my mouth:</hi> yea more then hony vnto my taſt, <hi>thy teſtimonies haue</hi> I <hi>taken as an heritage for euer,</hi> no earthly thing being compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to them, for they are the ioy of my heart, <hi>they that know thy law
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:7856:39"/> haue great proſperitie,</hi> and they ſhal haue no hurt. <hi>Keepe them and doe them</hi> (ſayth <hi>Moſes) for this is your wiſedome,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 4.6.8.9.</note> 
                  <hi>and vnderſtanding in the ſight of other people, who ſhal ſay, one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this people is wiſe, and what na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is ſo great that hath ordinances and lawes ſo righteous: therefore take heede to thy ſelfe, and keepe thy ſoule diligently: let not theſe things depart out of thy heart all the dayes of thy life, but teach them thy ſonnes, and thy ſonnes ſonnes.</hi> Hence procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth all bleſſings from heauen and earth, vpon man and beaſt, corne and cattell, wine, oyle, or what can be deſired,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.8.</note> 
                  <hi>for godlineſſe hath the promiſe of this life, and of the life to come.</hi> If we ſeeke the kingdome of God and his righteouſneſſe, all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things ſhall be miniſtred vnto vs:<note place="margin">Mat. 6.33. Mat. 13.44.45.46. Luke 10.42.</note> this is the beſt part and moſt neceſſary duty that cauſed <hi>Marie</hi>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:7856:39"/> to be preferred before <hi>Martha,</hi> for ſetting all other things aſide,<note place="margin">Hauing ſuch promiſes let vs with Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie chooſe the beſt part which ſhall neuer be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from vs.</note> to come ſit at Ieſus feete, to heare his word: this Pearle muſt be pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed with all wee haue, all other things are but droſſe and dung in reſpect of the excellent knowledg of Chriſt Ieſus our Lord, therfore we muſt not only heare and reade, and meditate, but encreaſe our loue, liking, and delight, to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly miniſtry of Gods word, lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging and thirſting after it,<note place="margin">Pſal. 42.1.2</note> with <hi>Dauid, As the Hart panteth after the water brookes, ſo panteth my ſoule after thee O God.</hi> Thus euery good Chriſtian muſt whet the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite of his ſoule to delight in Gods law, by conference, medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, hearing, reading, praying, preaching, and dayly frequenting of holy aſſemblyes:<note place="margin">Pſal. 122.1.</note> 
                  <hi>I was glad when they ſayd vnto mee, let vs goe
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:7856:40"/> into the houſe of the Lord.</hi> So was it propheſied of the chriſtian church that many people ſhould go and ſay,<note place="margin">Mich. 4.1.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">Eſa. 2.3. Eſa. 60.7.</note> 
                  <hi>Come let vs goe vp to the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of the Lord, to the houſe of the God of Iacob, and he will teach vs his wayes, and we ſhal walke in his paths: who are theſe that flie like a cloude, and as Doues to their windoes?</hi> No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting not onely the greatneſſe of the number, but diligence and zeale of ſuch as ſhould come to Chriſt and receiue his doctrine: and Chriſt ſayd,<note place="margin">Mat. 11.12.</note> that <hi>from the time of</hi> Iohn <hi>Baptiſt hitherto the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen ſuffereth violence, and the violent take it by force.</hi> Thus the zeale of Gods houſe ſhould eate vs vp.<note place="margin">The leaſt danger or weakneſſe doth put of ſuch as are backward in Gods ſeruice.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, this ſerueth to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute and reproue all ſuch as are backeward and careleſſe in this neceſſary duty, being idle and
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:7856:40"/> vaine in their excuſes or reaſons, to hinder their zeale and loue to the word, any feare, the leaſt danger,<note place="margin">Prou. 22.13 Pſa. 119.51 &amp; 62.7.11.12. Luk. 14.18.19.20.23.23.</note> and worldly buſineſſe doth put them off, <hi>There is a Lion in the way.</hi> Some haue their oxen to prooue, their Farme to ſee, their wife to marry, all theſe yet are inuited to come to the Feaſt, though vnworthy of the ſame: therefore God will fill his houſe with any others then with ſuch, euen thoſe that ſit in the high way and vnder hedges: the moſt ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt and vileſt of men ſhall enter before them and bee ſaued,<note place="margin">Mat. 21.31.32.</note> euen whores and harlots ſhall ſooner be receiued, then thoſe that ſeeme children of the kingdome: God will raiſe vp to <hi>Abraham</hi> ſonnes of ſtones rather then theſe vipe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ſerpents ſhall haue the name of his ſeed.<note place="margin">Mat. 3.9.</note>
               </p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:7856:41"/>
               <p>Others there are that thinke; if we ſhould make conſcience of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, &amp; begin to read the word, to frequent ſermons, to haue pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in our families, and the like; this would make vs to bee ſcoffed, and mocked at: but let ſuch heare what the word ſaith, that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounces them bleſſed that delight in the law of the Lord,<note place="margin">Pſalme 1.</note> and medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate therein day and night, and that ſeeke him with their whole hearts: yea albeit they ſhould meet with ſome diſgrace and oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the world.<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">Math. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Bleſſed are yee</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>when men reuile you, and perſecute you and ſpeake all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of euill againſt you falſly for my names ſakt. Reioyce and be glad, for great is your reward in heauen:</hi> is it not better to endure a little mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from men for a time, and that for well doing, then to vndergoe the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:7856:41"/> wrath of God for euer for ill do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Let vs conſider in particular what benefit we may reape by the miniſtry of the Goſpel:<note place="margin">Iſai 5.3.</note> 
                  <hi>Heare,</hi> ſaith the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iam. 1.21.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp; thy ſoule ſhal liue: receiue the word with meekenes</hi> (ſaith <hi>Iames) which is able to ſaue your ſoules:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reu. 1.3.</note> 
                  <hi>bleſſed is he that reades &amp; heares the words of this Propheſie</hi> ſaith the ſpirit in the Reuelation. And on the other ſide:<note place="margin">Prou. 28.9.</note> 
                  <hi>he that tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth away his eare from hearing the law, his prayer ſhall bee abomination,</hi> ſaith <hi>Salomon:</hi> and againe, the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God ſpeaks thus, <hi>becauſe I haue called, and ye refuſed;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prou 1.24.25.26.</note> 
                  <hi>I haue ſtretched out my hand,</hi> &amp; <hi>none would regard: but yee haue deſpiſed all my counſell, and would none of my cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection; I will alſo laugh at your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, and mocke when your feare commeth.</hi> Theſe and the like places, if wee could throughly
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:7856:42"/> conſider of, they would worke more powerfully with vs to cauſe vs to deſire the word, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and keepe our hearts ſtill in loue and liking of it, then all the reproches and perſecutions in the world could, to withdraw our affections from it.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">God is to be heard be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any.</note>Therefore they that come to receiue benefit by the miniſtery muſt not harken what reaſons fleſh and bloud can yeeld them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, but what reaſons God can giue them for it; for the diuell will haue much to ſay againſt goodneſſe, and our owne fleſhly wiſdome will haue haue as much, &amp; the world will be as great a pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>backe vnto vs if we will giue it the hearing, but if we can bend an at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiue eare vnto the Lord, wee ſhall finde that hee will bring bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter arguments to perſwade vs to
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:7856:42"/> goodneſſe, then all thoſe our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies can to diſſwade vs from it: &amp; therefore it is that men are ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and ſo groſſely deceiued, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they heare what the one ſide can ſay to diſcourage and hinder them in actions of piety and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, but not what the other can ſay to harten and draw them on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in good wayes: for if they did bring a ſpirituall eare to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the proofes that are brought from the word, they would be more forceable to bring them to God, then al other means could be to allure them to forſake God,<note place="margin">Eph. 4.30. If wee cher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh in vs the gifts of Gods holy ſpirit, it aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures vs of deliuerance from the wrath to come.</note> and to embrace or hearken to the allurements of this preſent world: &amp; therefore <hi>Paul</hi> writing to the Epheſians, he ſaith thus, <hi>grieue not the holy ſpirit of God nor that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly delight in the commandements:</hi> &amp; he brings a forcible reaſon, <hi>wherby
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:7856:43"/> you are ſealed vnto the day of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption.</hi> This is the onely eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence wee haue of freedome from condemnation, this is Gods marke and character ſet on vs, and ſeizing vs for his owne, this is like the blood that was ſtric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vpon the doore poſts,<note place="margin">Exo. 12.22</note> which ſhall make the Lord to paſſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vs, and not ſuffer the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyer to come neare vs when he goeth to ſmite the Egyptians. By this wee are aſſured that the day of iudgement ſhall bee to vs no day of wrath, but a day of redemption: ſo then thus wee may take the Apoſtles mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; as you deſire to retaine aſſurance of your deliuerance from the wrath to come, and that the Lord ſhould take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of you for his in the day of that dreadfull ſeparation, ſo
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:7856:43"/> ſee that by all meaanes you che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh in you the gifts and ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Gods holy ſpirit, grieue it not by ſtrangling and choa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of thoſe holy motions and operations, but let them be che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed and preſerued without any the leaſt abatement.</p>
               <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">Let vs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the motions of the ſpirit, for the ſin is fearefull.</note> this ſerueth to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne ſuch as nip the bud ſo ſoon as euer it peepeth foorth, and quench euery ſparke that at any time appeareth, yea, wilfully ſet themſelues to repell all good mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, haſting to their curſed company, to chaſe away thoſe ſweet inſpirements of Gods holy ſpirit. Oh the curſed vnthanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe of theſe men, what vnkind ingrateful; diſcourteous dealing is here with the ſpirit of grace, thus ſhutting him out ſo ſoone as euer he begins to enter:<note place="margin">Reuel. 3.20</note> wouldeſt thou
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:7856:44"/> deale ſo vnkindly with thy friend, who commeth to thy doore? why dealeſt thou then ſo vncourteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with Chriſt Ieſus and his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpirit,<note place="margin">Reuel. 3.20</note> who ſtandeth at the doore and dayly knockes, but can get no entertainement,<note place="margin">Act. 7.15.</note> beware of this reſiſting the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, the ſinne is fearfull and diſcomfortable, for here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by thy heart may grow more ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>durat, and thy life more brutiſh and abhominable.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, let euery one of vs beware how wee ſuffer that bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed heate to ſlacke,<note place="margin">This de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>light muſt ſhew it ſelfe by encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</note> which by Gods grace beginneth to bee inkindled in our hearts. Suffer not that coale, that holy motion which the Lord hath caſt into thy boſome to die within thee, but blow it vp, lay on more fuell, adde dayly more and more matter
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:7856:44"/> to it, and tremble to loſe the leaſt meaſure of Gods gracious gift: be frequent in ſpirituall exerciſes, as in hearing, reading, meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Chriſtian conference, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and the like: Let no meanes be neglected, that God hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained for the working of eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment. And as thou layeſt on fuell, ſo ſee thou giueſt this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Fire vent, exerciſe and put theſe holy motions into practiſe: much Wood piled on a Cole, if vent be wanting, doth ſoone ſmother it, &amp; put it out, ſee the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou exerciſe the graces w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> God hath giuen thee.</p>
               <p>Therefore when the Lord ſhall put any good motion into our hearts,<note place="margin">Good mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are-not to bee qvenched, but cheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed.</note> we are to nouriſh and che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rrſh the ſame: to one good moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on wee muſt adde a ſecond, and to that a third, and ſo fall to blowing, and giue not ouer
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:7856:45"/> vntill at length they breake forth into a comfortable flame of godly practiſes.<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 5.19.</note> 
                  <hi>Quench not the Spirit</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi>) nor the gifts and motions of the holy Ghoſt: hee vſed a Metaphor borrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from fire, whoſe heate and light when it is put out, is ſaid to bee quenched: Thus alſo hee exhorts <hi>Timothy</hi> to ſtir vp the graces of God which bee in him.<note place="margin">2. Tim. 1.6.</note> Thus it is with them that liue the life of Grace, there is a dayly ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king after foode, for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing of it,<note place="margin">Pſal. 1.2.</note> a dayly vſing of the meanes, as Prayer, Reading, Meditation; and thus it is ſaid of the bleſſed man: In Gods Law hee doth exerciſe himſelfe both day and night. Many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples might bee brought for proofe of this.</p>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:7856:45"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iob</hi> roſe vp early to offer ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, this did <hi>Iob</hi> continually:<note place="margin">Iob. 1.5.</note> and it was <hi>Daniels</hi> practiſe to pray three times a day: and <hi>Dauids: Euening,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dan. 6.10. Pſal. 55.17. Pſa. 119.164. Gen. 24.63</note> 
                  <hi>Morning, and Noone-tide, will I pray vnto thee:</hi> Yea, we may heare him ſpeaking of ſeuen times a day prayſing of the Lord: And <hi>Iſaac</hi> went into the Field to pray and meditate in the Euening.<note place="margin">Let vs ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine our ſelues in this duty, how we perform it in our practiſes.</note> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let euery Chriſtian man and woman try and examine them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in this duty: For it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely true, and cannot deceiue vs, that our prayers are proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onable to our faith: For hee that prayeth ſeldome hath but a weake faith; he that prayes often hath a ſtrong Faith; and he that prayes not at all hath no faith: For,<note place="margin">Rom. 10.10</note> 
                  <hi>with the heart man beleeueth vnto righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, and with the mouth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion is made vnto ſaluation.</hi> Let
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:7856:46"/> this be well conſidered of ſuch as heare, and reade, and pray by fits and ſtarts, now and then, as it were vpon rainy dayes. Alas, thouſands there are in the World, who reade not, pray not, from Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath to Sabbath; nay, nor then neither, haue theſe any life of grace in them? Sure I am, natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall life muſt be dayly fed, and ſhal be too, and is there not as much neede for the ſpirituall: be it ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore knowne vnto thee, and certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied to thy ſoule,<note place="margin">We ſhould let no day paſſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, nor ſuffer our eyes to ſlumber, nor our head to take any reſt tell we haue made peace with our God.</note> that thou decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt thy ſelfe, in thinking thou li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt the life of a Chriſtian, when there is no care had to a dayly performance of the excerciſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to a Chriſtian: therefore let no day paſſe ouer without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination, let vs call to mind what euils hath beene committed, what good duties omitted, which
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:7856:46"/> God hath required: ſuffer not thy eyes to ſlumber, nor the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of thy head to take any reſt, till this taske bee performed. Would Chriſtians keepe this courſe, and well conſider of their carriages the day paſt, they would ſoone find the excellent commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities of it, to the vnſpeakea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble comfort of their ſoules for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermore.</p>
               <p>Laſtly,<note place="margin">Phil. 3.13.</note> let this admoniſh eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one to grow in grace, let vs for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get that which is behinde, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour to that which is before; let vs preſſe hard towards the marke for the priſe of the high calling of God, let vs not bee euermore as ſmoaking flaxe, or bruiſed reeds, or as new ſet Plants, but let vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound more and more.<note place="margin">Theſ. 4.1.</note> At a ſtay we cannot ſtand, iudge what wee will, not to goe forward, is to go
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:7856:47"/> backward, not to encreaſe is to decreaſe, like as the Sunne, we are euermore in motion, and as the Sea,<note place="margin">Gen. 19, 26. Pſal. 114.3. Eccle. 1.</note> ebbing or flowing, and as the Angell on <hi>Iacobs</hi> Ladder, aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, or deſcending, therefore we muſt not looke backeward with <hi>Lots</hi> Wife, but forward with <hi>Lot</hi> himſelfe, nor ſtart backe as <hi>Iordan</hi> did, but runne forward as other Riuers doe, and trauell towards <hi>Canaan,</hi> with <hi>Caleb</hi> and <hi>Ioſua,</hi> ſo that ſtill we muſt profit in the way of godlineſſe, there muſt bee no growing downeward, but grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vpward;<note place="margin">Luke 2.52.</note> the Child Ieſus grew not downeward but vpward in grace, wiſedome, and ſtature, they which will haue their growth in Chriſt and towards his Kingdome muſt grow vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward:<note place="margin">Pſal. 84.7.</note> Let vs therefore pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede in ſanctfication, and goe
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:7856:47"/> from ſtrength to ſtrength,<note place="margin">Rom. 15.14.</note> and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour euery day to abound more and more in all wiſedome, and in goodneſſe. If wee prayed once a day in priuate, and that ſomewhat coldly at the firſt; we muſt after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward pray twice or thrice, or oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner in a day, as occaſion is offered; and that more feruently and fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly then wee did in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, if we did heare and meditate more ſeldome, and with greater weakeneſſe and diſtraction at our firſt entrance into profeſſion, in our proceeding we muſt vſe thoſe exerciſes more frequently,<note place="margin">We muſt grow in grace, and neuer reſt vntill we come to perfection.</note> and performe them more ſeriouſly &amp; cheerefully: So that if you bee in Chriſt, neuer reſt vntill you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſtrong in Chriſt; nay, if you bee in Chriſt, you will not reſt till you come to ſome perfection in him.<note place="margin">2. Pet. 1.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Ioyne therfore vnto your vertue
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:7856:48"/> faith, &amp; with faith knowledge, &amp; with knowledge temperance, &amp; with tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance patience, and with patience godlineſſe, and with godlineſſe bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly kindneſſe; for if theſe bee in you, they will make you neither vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitfull nor vnprofitable.</hi> Keepe then thy grace in an honeſt heart, and it will encreaſe like the Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes oyle in the Cruiſe, and meale in the Barrell, till thou come to be a perfect man in Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The markes of an vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right heart, is vniuerſall obedience.</note>Now wee are come to the laſt part of this bleſſed mans delight, and that is ſaid here to bee in the Commandements, and therefore that we may make ſure worke in this regard, let vs try our ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty by the good effects that doe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer accompany the ſame: The firſt note therefore of a ſound heart, which wee ſhould take for
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:7856:48"/> our tryall, is to bee vniuerſall in our deſires, and in our practiſe, that wee haue reſpect to euery Commandement of God,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.8.</note> to the firſt table, as well as to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, and to the ſecond as well as to the firſt, that we bee righteous towards men, as well as religious towards God, that wee looke to our hearts as well to our actions, and to our actions as well as to our hearts. Contrary to this rule is the dealing of thoſe that will giue diſpenſations vpon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues for many things, ſo that they can make a ſhew of ſome things: what if we be not ſo libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall to the poore, ſay they, yet we are no ſwearers nor blaſphemers; what if wee take a little liberty, theſe are but trifles; wee will not bee adulterers nor filthy ſpeakers, &amp;c, this is a ſhrewd ſigne of a
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:7856:49"/> heart full fraught with guile and deceit- The property of a good conſcience is to bee willing and deſirous in all things to walke ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly:<note place="margin">Heb. 13.18.</note> if one be neuer ſo ſtrickt in hearing Sermons, and abſtaining from ſwearing: yet if he will helpe himſelfe with a lye now and then, for his commodity; and if a man bee neuer ſo rigorous and ſeuere for matters of Iuſtice againſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, yet will diſpenſe with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in a corner, thinking that the name of a Profeſſor, and reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the brotherhood will beare him out, this is an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a falſe and diſſembling heart, &amp; therfore this muſt be taken heed of, as being very dangerous.</p>
               <p>Therefore that we may not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue our ſelues in this one tryall, the ſincere and honeſt heart, as our Sauiour calls it, is that which
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:7856:49"/> cheriſheth hatred of all ſin, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out exception, and carrieth a conſtant purpoſe and reſolution in nothing willingly to ſinne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, but to endeauour it ſelfe to the vtmoſt in euery good way of Gods Commandements: Whatſoeuer it ſhall know to be a ſinnes, it will not purpoſely and deliberately do it for al the world: this note the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, for hauing ſaid:<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.3.</note> 
                  <hi>Bleſſed are the vpright in their way,</hi> hee teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vs to diſcerne them by this note: <hi>Surely they doe no iniquity. With my whole heart haue I ſought thee,</hi> ſaith <hi>Dauid,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.10</note> 
                  <hi>ſuffer mee not to wander from thy Commandements:</hi> Inſinuating thereby, that ſuch as doe not ſeeke God with their whole hearts, that is, in ſinglenes of heart vnfainedly, God will ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer them to wander in crooked
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:7856:50"/> blind wayes, and that fearefully &amp; irrecouerably. To the like pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe is that in the ſame Pſalme, <hi>Let my heart be vpright in thy ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, that</hi> I <hi>may neuer be aſhamed.</hi> And although Saint <hi>Iames</hi> ſay,<note place="margin">Iam. 3.3.2.</note> 
                  <hi>In many things we offend all:</hi> yet wee muſt reſolue our ſelues to leaue all ſin: For if we liue &amp; lie but in one ſin, that one ſin is ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to preſſe vs down to hel:<note place="margin">Can. 4.7.</note> therfore the ſpouſe is ſaid to haue no ſpot in her, for if ſhe had but one ſpot, then were ſhe not beautiful in his eyes; let the walls of the City bee neuer ſo ſtrong, if there be one breach, the enemy will enter in, and ſacke the City, if a ſtrong ſhip do but leake in one place, it will be drowned, a beaſt which is caught in the ſnare but by one leg cannot eſcape, one Flie falling into the Apothecaries boxe will ſpoyle the whole oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.<note place="margin">2. Sam. 15.</note> Let vs remember <hi>Saul,</hi> and
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:7856:50"/> forget not our owne ſoules, God co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded him vtterly to deſtroy the <hi>Amalekites,</hi> he ſparing but ſome of them, was caſt off from God, &amp; his Kingdome rent from him: our ſinnes are the ſinnes of the <hi>Amale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kites,</hi> which God co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeth vs to deſtroy, we muſt kill them all, and ſpare none, leſt God forſake vs, &amp; ſo we loſe a better Kingdom then euer <hi>Saul</hi> found: For,<note place="margin">Iam. 2.10. Iam. 1.17. Heb. 12.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Whoſoeuer ſhal keep the whole Law, &amp; yet offend in one point, he is guilty of all, for pure religion and vndefiled, is to keep our ſelues vnſpotted of the world.</hi> Let vs therfore caſt euery ſin away, which is as great weight,<note place="margin">This diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers many to be lewd and diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute perſons when the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements are diſtaſtfull vnto them.</note> and lay aſide e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery ſin with which we are beſet.</p>
               <p>Firſt, this ſerueth for the diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery of many, to be the ſonnes of <hi>Beliall,</hi> lawleſſe, lewd, and diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute perſons, to whom nothing is more grieuous then Gods go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:7856:51"/> and nothing more diſtaſtfull then the Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Lord: Gods Word is like hard meate lying heauy vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſtomacke, that cannot eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bee digeſted, thoſe precepts gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, for the ordering of our waies: <hi>Sweare not at all,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 5.34.</note> 
                  <hi>ſanctifie my Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both,</hi> they are hard ſayings, who can endure them; nay, they could wiſh they were raſed out of the booke, and there were no ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction: debar them from ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, you were as good ſowe vp their lippes; keepe them from their ſports on the Sabbath day, why then take away their liues; nay, they cannot nor will not bee ſo ſtraight laced, their ſports they muſt follow, their pleaſures they muſt take, and no day fitter then that, thus <hi>Sampſon</hi> like, they break Gods Lawes, like twind threds,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:7856:51"/> and ſay: <hi>Depart from vs, wee will none of thy wayes.</hi> Let all ſuch then know, that pretend what they will, they are but lawleſſe perſons, children of <hi>Belial,</hi> who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire nothing more, then to be from vnder Gods Commandements, and to caſt his yoke from off their necks: therefore I may truely ſay, that where the Sabbath is not ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified, there is neither ſound Religion nor a Chriſtian con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation. How God eſteemeth the ſanctification of the Sabbath, may appeare by the exact deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Commandements, for he hath fenced it about like Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 19.12</note> with markes and bounds at the deliuery of the Law, that no prophaneneſſe might approach neere vnto you; firſt, by his watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>word, <hi>Remember;</hi> ſecondly,<note place="margin">Exo. 20.8, 9</note> by his bounty, <hi>ſixe dayes thou ſhalt labour,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:7856:52"/> and doe all that thou haſt to doe;</hi> thirdly, by his ſoueraignty, <hi>It is the Sabbath of the Lord thy God;</hi> fourthly, by the latitude, <hi>thou, thy ſon thy daughter, thy man ſeruant, thy maid ſeruant, the ſtranger that is within thy gates</hi> muſt ſanctifie it; fiftly, by his example, <hi>The Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted the ſeuenth day;</hi> laſtly, by his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nediction, <hi>he bleſſed and ſanctified it.</hi> Theſe ſixe markes are like the ſixe Water-pots in the ſecond of <hi>Iohn,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn 2.7. Let euery one of vs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member to ſanctifie the Lords Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, &amp; that ſhall bee a pledge of the eternall Sabbath in the kingdom of Heauen.</note> fill them vp to the brim with a holy obſeruation, then draw out &amp; carry to the maſter of the feaſt, euen to Ieſus Chriſt, the Lord of the new Sabbath: therefore let vs remember to ſanctifie the Lords Sabbath, and that ſhall be vnto vs a pledge of the eternal Sabbath in the kingdome of Heauen, which ſhal be a day without euening, &amp; ſhal yeeld vs reſt without labor, &amp; ioy without ending.</p>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:7856:52"/>
               <p>Secondly, behold a difference,<note place="margin">There is great diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the godly and the wicked in their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience.</note> whereby wee may try our ſelues, betweene the wicked and the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the one deſires to draw in Gods yoke, and yeeld obedience to the commandements; and the other deſires nothing more then to caſt it of: let vs examine then how our heart is affected, doeſt thou finde this inward diſcontentment in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beying? are Gods lawes as bonds and cords in thy eſteeme? and as a ſtomackful horſe doſt thou foame at the bit which is put into thy mouth; an euident ſigne of a rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious heart: but one the other ſide, art thou content to ſubmit thy ſelf to Gods commandements? art thou deſirous that thy nature would bee more conformable to Gods law? art thou content to be reſtrained, and if it were poſſible to haue the wicked inclination of
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:7856:53"/> thy heart aboliſhed? ſurely then thou needeſt not to want comfort, thy ſtate will affoord it, goe on therefore conſtantly vnto the end.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Here is great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort for all ſuch as find vprightnes in their harts thogh they haue many imper<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fections.</note>Thirdly, here is great conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for all ſuch as find theſe notes of vprightneſſe in themſelues, and that they haue part in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements: though they haue many corruptions and imperfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions mixed with their beſt works; yet ſeeing they haue pure hearts, they are happy and bleſſed, and ſhall find the good effects of their bleſſedneſſe, true holineſſe, and true happineſſe are neuer ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. As for perfections, God looks not for it at our hands, if ſinne hang on vs, but wee would faine caſt it off, if we finde vnbeleefe, but would moſt gladly get faith if wee bee troubled in our hearts with hardneſſe, but are deſirous of
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:7856:53"/> ſoftneſſe, if we be humbled for that we cannot be humbled ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, nor get ſuch a large heart as we would to deſire and exſpect grace from heauen, yet let vs not be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comforted for our defects and frailties for the Lord will ſpare vs and be gratious vnto vs in his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued ſonne, according to that worthy prayer of good king <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiah;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Chro. 30.18.19.</note> 
                  <hi>The good Lord be mercifull toward him that prepared his whole heart to ſeeke the Lord God of his fathers, though he be not cleanſed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the purification of the ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuarie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, this ſerueth for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to the children of God,<note place="margin">Our good purpoſes ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded.</note> to let them ſee how highly God prizeth good purpoſes and deſires, accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and rewarding them when they come to him, as if they came accompanyed with the deedes
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:7856:54"/> themſelues. <hi>Dauid</hi> did but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue a purpoſe to build God a houſe,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 7.16</note> God rewards it with the building and eſtabliſhing of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uids</hi> houſe: hee did but conceiue a purpoſe to confeſſe his ſinnes, Gods eare was in his heart before <hi>Dauids</hi> confeſſion could bee in his tongue.<note place="margin">Pſal. 32.5.</note> The poore beggers that haue wanted food for themſelues, Chriſt yet ſhall ſay at the laſt day, <hi>Ye haue fed mee when I was hungry,</hi> onely in regard of their ſtrong af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection if they had had abilitie:<note place="margin">Luk. 15.20.</note> the prodigall child when hee was but conceiuing a purpoſe of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning, was preuented by his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers firſt comming to him,<note place="margin">Iſa. 65.24.</note> and as <hi>Iſay</hi> ſayth, <hi>God will anſwer vs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we call,</hi> that is in our purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of prayer. O ſweete com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort when wee addreſſe our ſelues to prayer in our priuate
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:7856:54"/> meditations, and bethinke our ſelues of our ſundry wants, we purpoſe with our ſelues to beg ſuch and ſuch things, whereof yet happily wee forget ſome in the vocall prayer; ſhall any good ſoule now thinke that the memories weakeneſſe ſhall any thing preiudice her in this caſe? no, thy purpoſe of asking the thing forgotten was a moſt effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall asking of it,<note place="margin">Therefore when the Lord ſhall put any good mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions into our mind, let vs not delay but ſpeedily put them in practiſe.</note> and vnto thee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth the comfort of that ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>I will heare before they calll.</hi> Therefore ſeeing the Lord doth ſo highly eſteeme good purpoſes, let vs not delay, but ſpeedily put then in practiſe. Before the Iron coole it is good ſtriking, &amp; while the waxe is plyable it is good ſetting on the Seale, doeſt thou then feele at any time that thy heart is warmed with good
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:7856:55"/> motions, enlarged with good af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, lift vp to heauen in ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall meditations: doeſt thou feele any ſparkles of the heauenly fire? take, take thou the bellowes pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently, blow till the flame cheriſh in thee, and make much of the ſmoking flaxe:<note place="margin">Eccleſ 5.31.</note> and therefore what <hi>Salomon</hi> exhorteth in the caſe of vowes, is generally to be practiſed in all holy purpoſes and motions; bee not ſlacke to performe them, they that know themſelues, know how fickle and vnconſtant their hearts are: now as we would deale with a variable and vnconſtant man, ſo let vs deale with theſe hearts of ours: we would take ſuch a one at his word, and lay hold of the opportunity, leaſt within a ſhort ſpace he alter his minde: our hearts are more vnconſtant then any man is or can be; let vs then
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:7856:55"/> learne this wiſedome, preſently to lay hold of euery good motion, and put it in practiſe, do not ſtand debating the matter when God putteth any good thought into thy heart, or rayſeth vp any good purpoſe or deſire within thee, but preſently proceed to execution, make no long tarrying before thou doeſt put them in action: there haue beene many who haue reſolued to leaue ſuch a ſinne,<note place="margin">Delaying of time very dangerous.</note> or doe ſuch a dutie, and put in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe what they haue heard, but by reaſon of their deferring vntill the next day, or ſuch a time, thoſe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions die, and purpoſes vaniſh, and come to nothing for want of ſpeedy execution.<note place="margin">The right way to try our ſelues is to know that wee haue forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken our ſins</note>
               </p>
               <p>And therefore let vs trye our ſelues if theſe good purpoſes haue wrought in vs a forſaking of ſinne, and a reformation of life: if it bee
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:7856:56"/> thus, then it is well; for this it is, &amp; muſt bee with euery true penitent. True it is in the time of our impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitency, like wilde and mad horſes we gallop in the way of ſinne, yet in the day of our repentance the ſpirit of God as with a bit or bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle giueth vs a checke, and turnes vs backe, and ſetteth vs as faſt a going the other way, inſomuch that our olde companions ſtand wondering at the matter, admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that wee ſo ſuddenly breake off company,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 4.4.</note> and runne not with them to the ſame exceſſe of ryot: ſo great is the change, that not onely our ſelues, but others alſo ſee it &amp; admire it. Now then, thou that talkeſt of repentance, and of thy obedience to the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, is this change in thee; aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure thy ſelfe, if thou haſt repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, it is, and all the world may ſee
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:7856:56"/> it. Canſt thou with a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſay of thy ſelfe, as <hi>Paul</hi> did of the Corinthians:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 6.10.11.</note> 
                  <hi>I was once a thiefe a drunkard, an adulterer, a reuiler, an extortioner, a couetous perſon,</hi> and the like: <hi>but now I am waſhed, now I am ſanctified, yea, iuſtified in the name of the Lord Ieſus,</hi> and by the ſpirit of my God; canſt thou thus ſay of thy ſelfe, and that in truth? why then to thy comfort be it ſpoken, this is a notable eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the truth of thy repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; but if it be otherwiſe, thou mayeſt deceiue thy ſelfe, for if no reformation followes, theſe are not ſignes of true repentance, <hi>for this is true repentance,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſtine.</note> ſaith <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine, ſo to bewayle ſinnes paſt, as that we commit them no more, which wee haue bewayled.</hi> It is to no purpoſe then for vs to bewayle our former courſes, vnleſſe there
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:7856:57"/> follow amendment: let not then this deceiue thee,<note place="margin">For where the Lord giues repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, there he giues the grace of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocation, whereby they becom new crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</note> 
                  <hi>for thou doeſt but mocke, and not indeed repent, when thou ſtill doeſt that whereof thou haſt repented, this is true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, ſo to repent, that thou haſt ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, as that thou doeſt ſo no more:</hi> till therfore thou doeſt ceaſe from ſinne and reforme thy wayes, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till thou doeſt find this change in thy ſelfe, ſo that thou canſt truely ſay I was thus and thus, but now the caſe is altered, thou canſt haue no comfort in thy repentance, nor in the commandements: for aſure thy ſelfe that repentance and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance in the old wicked cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes can neuer ſtand together.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, this may ſerue for the comfort of all ſuch as doe finde this change in themſelues, who can ſay with that blinde man who had his ſight reſtored, one thing
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:7856:57"/> know, that whereas I was blinde, now I ſee;<note place="margin">Ioh. 9.25.</note> whereas I was filthy and vncleane, I am now waſhed and cleanſed: Oh happy is the condition of ſuch a one, thriſe bleſſed is the eſtate of that man: onely manifeſt this change vnto the world, that others may alſo ſay; How is this man cbanged from what he was? that as others haue beene witneſſes of thy ſinne, ſo they may bee alſo witneſſes of thy repentance.</p>
               <p>This may ſerue for reproofe,<note place="margin">Looſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooued as being farre from kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements.</note> againſt our looſe and leud hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, masked vnder the name of pure profeſſors, promiſing to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, though liuing and lying in their ſins, &amp; far fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> keeping the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mants, the reward of glory, no, as thou ſoweſt thou muſt reape, &amp; as thou brueſt thou muſt drinke, if thou ſowe tares, neuer looke to
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:7856:58"/> reape wheate; if thou Brue with crabs, neuer looke to drinke milde Beere. Can men gather figges of thorns, or grapes of thiſtles: ſo I comparing our workes to trees, their rewards to the fruits; ſay the like: thinke you euer of the thorns and thiſtles of couetouſnes, pride, vncleannes, blaſphemy, ſwearing, profanation of the Sabaoths, euer to gather the ſweet figges, or plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant grapes of glory and happines? will this gall and wormewood e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer make pleaſant drinke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, will theſe wilde and ſower grapes euer yeeld ſweete wine? Oh that wee could ſeriouſly lay this to heart; that <hi>wee muſt all appeare before the iudgement ſeat of Chriſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.10 11.</note> 
                  <hi>to receiue according to that which we here haue done, whether good or euill: that hee that ſoweth of the fleſh ſhall of the fleſh reape corruption,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 6.8.</note> 
                  <hi>and hee that
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:7856:58"/> ſoweth of the ſpirit, ſhall of the ſpirit reape life euerlaſting;</hi> then would we preſently begin to reaſon with our ſelues; Alas how poore, how how barren am I in good workes, how fruitfull in ill; it is true indeed that according to the quality of our works we ſhall be iudged; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las what other works can I preſent the Lord withal, beſides the works of death and darknes, if theſe had the promiſe of reward, then were my caſe good; let vs examine our hearts herein, and thinke euer with our ſelues, thus long haue I liued, but what good haue I done, eyther to my ſelfe or others? where are my prayers, faſtings, humiliations, meditations, well ſpent Saba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oths, well gouerned children, and ſeruants? where are the workes of mercie to my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:7856:59"/> either to their ſoules in holy admonition, reprehenſion, exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, or bodies in miniſtring re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe to their neceſſities; how can I look for the penny that hath ſtood idle in the market place, all the day long; for the crown, that refuſed to runne,<note place="margin">Rom. 2.7.</note> for a good crop in harueſt, that would not ſowe in ſeed time: let vs no longer deceiue our ſelues no glory, honor, and immortality can be found of any, but ſuch as ſeeke it by continuance in well doing and in keeping the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, and delighting therein.</p>
               <p>Seeing then the greater our zeal paines, and trauell hath beene in Gods cauſe, the greater ſhall bee weight of our glory: the twelue Apoſtles ſhall haue twelue ſpecial thrones at the day of iudgement: and whereas otherwiſe men ſhall
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:7856:59"/> but ſhine with the brightneſſe of the firmament,<note place="margin">Dan. 12 3.</note> they that turne o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers from their euill wayes, with brightneſſe of the ſtarres,<note place="margin">Phil. 4.17.</note> 
                  <hi>hee that ſoweth liberally ſhall reape liberally:</hi> and euery good worke added to the number of the former, helpeth to further our reckoning in the day of the Lord.<note place="margin">Mat. 12.</note> And here for our comfort let vs remember that <hi>God rewards euery one according to his worke,</hi> for he will reward the leaſt good worke, euen a cup of cold water,<note place="margin">ant. 5.1.</note> eating not onely of our ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, but of our hony-combe; yea at the laſt day notice will bee ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of inferiour ſorts of workes as giuing a peece of bread or a peece of cloath. God forbid then that any ſhould ſay with thoſe in <hi>Malachy, It is in vaine to ſerue the Lord,</hi> therefore let vs feare Gods ſaying, <hi>Behold
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:7856:60"/> I come quickely and my reward is with me.</hi> When <hi>Mordecay</hi> had performed a worthy ſeruice to <hi>Ahaſhueroſh</hi> in diſcouery of a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous treaſon,<note place="margin">Eſt. 6.10.</note> hee had not his reward preſently, but yet his ſeruice was regiſtred, and ſo af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward when the king looked vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the records, it was royally recompenced. <hi>Malachy</hi> teacheth vs that there are books of remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance written for them thar feare the Lord,<note place="margin">Mal. 3.16.</note> and in this Chronicle all our good ſeruices, euen euery action of obedience is recorded, that it may bee rewarded; our labour then ſhall not bee loſt, nor ſo much as our teares but they are blotted; men may forget vs as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> did <hi>Ioſeph,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iudg. 9.17. Gen. 41, 42.</note> and <hi>Sechemites, Gedeon,</hi> but God wil not, our reward is ſure though
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:7856:60"/> not ſo ſpeedy as wee deſire:<note place="margin">Here is great comfort to all faithfull Miniſters, who ſpend their ſtrength to turne ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners from their euill wayes, great is their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in Heauen. We muſt liue the life grace heare if we meane to ſhine in glory hereafter.</note> God heere aſſures vs of reward in the Kingdome of Heauen. Behold what comfort ſhineth from hence to all you who haue ſpent your ſtrength in the ſeruice of God, and conuerſion of ſinners, great is your reward in Heauen, you ſhall ſhine as ſtarres in the Ftrmament, for euer and euer.</p>
               <p>From hence we learne, that the degrees of glory heereafter, ſhall bee according to the degrees of grace here, ſo that if wee would then ſhine in glory, now we muſt ſhine in grace; therefore take the aduantage of this thy corruption, ſhake of all ſpirituall ſloth, vſe it as a goade in thy ſide, to make thee ſweat againe in Gods worke, dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble paines ſhall bring thee double pleaſure; double deligence, dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble delight; double holineſſe, dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:7856:61"/> honour: Who will be a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſtone in the building, when he might be a Piller? Who would be a Doore-keeper when he might be a Steward; therefore let vs looke to the whole courſe of our liues: God rewards vs not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our good or euill worke, but according to our workes, to the ordinary courſe of them: this muſt teach vs faithfully to walke before the Lord, in the diſcharge of our ſeuerall callings; let vs look well to our worke that wee doe it, and God will looke farre better to reward our worke. Oh then that inſtead of taking thought how to get this or that good thing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, wee would once take thought how to doe this or that good thing commanded, and ſo doing our duty, we ſhould be hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py for euermore.</p>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:7856:61"/>
               <p>In worldly affaires no weighty thing can bee done without dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, farre leſſe in ſpirituall. <hi>Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be he that doth the worke of the Lord negligently,</hi> how ſhall hee looke for the penny that hath ſtood idle: Oh that there were no ſuch to bee found in theſe our dayes,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 4, 2.</note> forgetting the rule of the Apoſtle: <hi>Preach in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon.</hi> Hence it commeth to paſſe, that their Sheepe belonging to their charge are like <hi>Pharoa</hi> his Kine, ſo leane and euill fauoured, and ſo weake as euery buſh is able to entangle, and euery ditch rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to drowne them, and euery blaſt of vaine Doctrine able to blow them away. Oh that this charge were conſidered, and that we remembred, that belongeth to them that preach not the Goſpell. Art thou a Steward? Art thou an
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:7856:62"/> Ambaſſador? Why then doſt thou not diſtribute Gods food vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his people? How wilt thou be able to looke him in the face, at whoſe barre one day all fleſh muſt ſtand?<note place="margin">Luke 16.21</note> and if the rich man were caſt into Hell, who did not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue poore <hi>Lazarus</hi> with his bread? What ſhall become of thoſe that haue famiſhed the Soules of their people, for want of holy admonition and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</p>
               <p>Firſt, to all bee it ſpoken, both Miniſter and people, let vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyd all ſinne, and endeauour our our ſelues to the vtmoſt of our power to keepe and delight in the Commandements, not one but al, and that we may not deceiue our ſelues herein, let euery man exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine himſelfe at this marke, and with a ſingle eye, and vpright
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:7856:62"/> heart take a view of his affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; whether his ioy bee inward and ſpirituall; that is, in the aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances of God fauour in his word, in his Children, in Prayer, and continuall practiſe of Godlineſſe, or outward and carnall; that is, in attainement of greatneſſe and worldly pleaſures, in the encreaſe of our Corne, and Wine, and Oyle: vvhether hee loue the peace of Conſcience, farre more dearely then the fauour of men, or his owne life: Whether hee bee more zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous for the honour and praiſe of GOD then his owne: Whether hee bee more afraid of ſecret ſinnes, then open ſhame of offending God, then outward afflictions: Whether he bee more angry in the cauſe of Religion, and concerning
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:7856:63"/> Gods glory, or for our owne pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate wrongs, and ſo throughout the reſt of our affections.</p>
               <p>Secondly, wouldeſt thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent thee of thy ſinnes, turne from them, and haue them pardoned, then labour to know them, ſtriue to find them out. Conſider of thy wayes, make a ſtand for a while, and examine thy courſes, put the queſtion to thy ſoule, what haue I done, and againe propound it, wherein am I fayling, take the light of Gods Law, that will ſhew thee thy filthineſſe, that will diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer vnto thee thy great corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and many faylings: bee not backward in this duty, the more backward thou art, the greater cauſe thou haſt to feare thy eſtate. Bankerouts that are not worth a groat do not dare look into their ſtate, becauſe they know they bee
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:7856:63"/> worſe then nought: bee then per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to call thy courſes to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count. Conſider the eſtate wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thou art, thy caſe is fearefull, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou art ignorant of it, but it is deſperate, if thou wilt not be perſwaded to looke into it; but on the other ſide, if thou wilt take thy ſelfe aſide, and commune with thy owne heart, as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeaketh,<note place="margin">Pſal. 4.4.</note> ſurely then thou wilt be in a fayre forwardneſſe to ſound conuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p>But heare ſome may aske,<note place="margin">Obedience to all the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements is an infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſigne of a true iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying faith.</note> how ſhall I know if I be ſuch a one or not? I anſwere, thou mayſt eaſily prooue it in keeping the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, and delighting therein; by this maiſt thou know, and therefore try thy ſelfe, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou haſt reſpect to the firſt Table as well as to the ſecond, &amp; to the ſecond as well as to the
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:7856:64"/> firſt? doſt thou performe good du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties for conſcience ſake, doſt thou as well make conſcience of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling with the world, defrau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thy neighbour, lying, or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiuocating for aduantage, as of blaſpheming Gods name, of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaning Gods Sabbath, of neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting holy exerciſes? Doſt thou lament and bewayle thy dulneſſe and deadneſſe, thy drowſineſſe and heauines in the performance of holy duties to God, and honeſt duties to men? Art thou grieued and diſquieted when thou findeſt not the efficacies and fruit of thoſe good exerciſes in thy heart? haſt thou learned to make conſcience of ſinnes of omiſſion, as well of commiſſion? Doſt thou as well open thy mouth to ſpeake to his honour, as keepe it ſhut from di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhonouring him? Doſt thou as
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:7856:64"/> well make conſcience of doing theſe good duties on the Sabbath Day, hearing, reading, medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and the like, which God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth, as thou doſt from abſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the workes of thy ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry calling, which hee forbiddeth? and doſt thou not reſt in Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues, abſtaining only from what is forbidden; but haſt thou alſo regard to affirmatiues, doing what God hath enioyned to bee done, eſteeming this latter as neceſſary as the former. Surely if it bee thus, thou mayſt haue comfort that thy obedience to the Commandements is ſound and good; but yet a little further: thou abſtaineſt from groſſe euils, and art ſeuere and ſore againſt others that fall into them, ſuch &amp; ſuch ſinnes thou doſt not commit, but what is the ground of thy ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaining?
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:7856:65"/> Is it the law of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, feare of Gods wrath or ſhame of the World, or is it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou wanteſt ability or op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity? if this be the ground, let me tell thee, this is a falſe ground, &amp; will deceiue thee in the end. But doſt thou leaue theſe,<note place="margin">H ſ. 3.5. Pſal. 130.4.</note> becauſe they are euill and diſpleaſing to the Lord: Doſt thou feare the Lord and his goodneſſe, and tremble to offend him becauſe of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy? Why then, it is an euident ſigne of a ſanctified ſoule. Oh that we would deale truely with our ſelues, that we would now at the laſt learne to be wiſe, and not gull our ſoules as moſt doe: and therefore conſider with thy ſelfe, and be thou better aduiſed, caſt of all profainenes, &amp; follow holines and piety, for without it no man ſhal euer ſee God to his comfort.
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:7856:65"/> Seeing therfore examination is ſo neceſſary for euery one,<note place="margin">Examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſo neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, that without it no ſtate of life can bee rightly orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</note> let vs goe one ſtep further in this tryall of our ſelues: Haſt thou felt by thine owne experience, this great worke of regeneration and change, wrought vpon thy ſoule? Hath the powerfull Word, by the inward and effectuall working of his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, broken and bruiſed thy hard &amp; ſtony heart? Hath it pierced and purged the very cloſeſt and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearchable corners thereof, hath it humbled it with the ſight of thy ſinnes, hath it filled it with feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full terrours, remorſe and true ſorrow for thy life paſt, hath it af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter quieted and refreſhed it with a ſure faith in Chriſt Ieſus, and a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in heauenly things, hath it mortified thy inward corruptions &amp; broke the heart of thy ſweet ſin, hath it planted a holy moderation
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:7856:66"/> in all thy affections, that whereas heretofore they haue beene enra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with luſt, with immoderate anger with ambition, with inſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able deſire, for the inlargement of thy poſſeſſions &amp; greatneſſe, and with hatred of Gods deareſt ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants and their holineſſe, are they now inflamed with zeale for Gods honor, truth &amp; ſeruice, with a fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent loue vnto the Lord and his Saints, with Chriſtian courage to oppoſe againſt the ſinnes of the time, to defend goodneſſe &amp; good cauſes, to contemne the lying ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and profane ſcoffes of worth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe men, hath it begot in thy will an hunger and thirſt after the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall foode of thy ſoule, the Word and Sacraments, ſo that thou hadſt rather part with any worldly good, then not enioy the incomparable benefit of a conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onable
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:7856:66"/> and conſtant miniſtery, are thy thoughts which hertofore did wander vp &amp; downe at randome wickedly, idly, wantonly, are they now bounded within a ſacred compaſſe, and ſpent vpon holy things, and the neceſſary affaires of thy honeſt &amp; lawfull calling? Is thy vnderſtanding informed &amp; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the miſtery of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which the world, &amp; the wiſe men thereof account nothing but madnes and folly, is thy memory which hath heretofore bin ſtuffed with traſh and toyes, vanities and follies, now capable and greedy of diuine knowledge, are thy words which heretofore haue bin full of profanenes &amp; worldlines, now di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to glorifie God, &amp; to giue grace to the hearers? Nay yet fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, beſides this reuocation of the faculties of thy ſoule, hath the
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:7856:67"/> power of grace ſanctified all thy outward actions? Doſt thou or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in euery particular all the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of thy vocation religiouſly, conſcionably, &amp; by direction out of the Word of God? Doſt thou now heare the Word of God, not only of courſe and cuſtome, but of zeale &amp; conſcience, to reforme thy ſelfe by it, &amp; to liue after it? Do not the weekdaies duties and worldly cares drown thy mind on the ſab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath? doſt thou exerciſe daily with fruit &amp; feeling, prayer, that preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort of the faithfull Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an? Thou being conuerted doſt thou labor the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſion of others, eſpecially of thoſe which are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted any way to thy charge, and for whom thou muſt giue a more ſtrickt account; as if thou be a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of a family, doſt thou pray with them, &amp; inſtruct them in the
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:7856:67"/> doctrine of ſaluation, &amp; wayes of godlineſſe? doſt thou now not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſticke at, and forbeare great and groſſe ſinnes, but doſt thou euen hate the garment ſpotted of the fleſh, and all appearance of euill?<note place="margin">Theſ. 15.22</note> doth the tendernes of thy conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence check thee for the leaſt ſin, &amp; make thee feareful to offend, thogh it be but in a wandring cogitation after euery fal into infirmities? art thou carefull to renew thy repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, &amp; learn wiſedom &amp; watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes to auoid the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> afterwards? doſt thou feele thy ſelfe profit, grow, &amp; increaſe in theſe fruits &amp; effects of grace, &amp; haſt thou ſuch a gracious taſte of the glory of God, &amp; of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life, that thou art euen willing &amp; deſirous to meete thy Sauior in the clouds, not ſo much to bee rid out of the miſeries of this life, as to be freed from the heauy burden of<note place="margin">Heb. 12.1.</note>
                  <pb n="120" facs="tcp:7856:68"/> ſin which hangs on ſo faſt, &amp; to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy his preſence in the heauens for euer; in a word, as thy ſoule giues life, ſpirit &amp; motion to thy whole body, &amp; euery part thereof, doth the Spirit of God, euen ſo inſpire thy ſoule and body, and all thy ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions with the life of grace? why then thou art poſſeſt of the ſtate of true bleſſednes:<note place="margin">Here is great comfort for all ſuch as can find this vprightneſſe in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, they neede not feare, thogh the earth ſhould bee mooued, yet they ſhall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide and be ſafe in the Day of the Lord.</note> thou art then hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py that euer thou waſt borne, thy life is certainely the way of life, and I can aſſure thee, and I dare boldly ſpeake it, that thou art al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready out of the reach of all the powers of Hell; Satan is chained vp for euer doing thee any dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hurt, all the creatures are recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled vnto thee, &amp; at league with thee, thou haſt filled the angels with ioy at thy conuerſion, they will for euer gard thee, thou ſhalt neuer more be afraid for any ill tidings,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:7856:68"/> though the earth bee moued,<note place="margin">Pſal. 46.2.</note> and though the mountains fal into the middeſt of the ſea, thy heart ſhall abide ſtrong, vnſhaken, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable: when thou falleſt downe vpon thy bed of ſickeneſſe, thou ſhalt finde no mortall pryſon in thy fleſh, no ſting in death, no darkeneſſe in the graue, no amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at that great and fearful day: for all the merits and ſufferings of Chriſt are thine, all the comforts of Gods children are thine, all the bleſſings in the booke of God are thine, euen all things are thine, and thou art Chriſts, and Chriſt is Gods: onely ſtand faſt in thy faith, quit thy ſelfe like a man and bee ſtrong, gird thy ſword vpon thy thigh, buckle faſt to thee the whole armour of God, ride on becauſe of the word of truth,<note place="margin">Pſal. 45.3.</note> and the Lord thy God bee with thee; breake
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:7856:69"/> through for a while with vndan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted courage the bitterneſſe of the worlds malice, the keene razours of empoyſoned tongs, the teares and tediouſnes of a few wretched daies, for thou art neerer the prize of the high calling, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> when thou firſt beleeuedſt: ſhine more and more in faith, in patience, in loue, in knowledge, in obedience, and all other chriſtian graces, vntill the perfect day, vntill thou reach the height of heauen, and the full glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Saints of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A true mark of our repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, if we haue left our euill wayes to ſerue the liuing God.</note>Firſt, here is matter of great conſolation for vs, for hereby wee may gather aſſurance vnto our owne hearts of the ſoundneſſe of our repentance, and conuerſion to the Lord, if we haue indeede tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from our euill wayes to ſerue the liuing God, ſo that we delight in the commandements: therefore
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:7856:69"/> they may take this for their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, who are ſtill propoſing of good queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, what they muſt do, and how they muſt do it, by what meanes they may get out of this or that ſinne, and attaine to ſuch or ſuch a grace, how they may bee profitable, helpfull, and comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to themſelues and others: this was the practiſe of the Publicans and Souldiers, and all ſorts that were inwardly touched in their conſciences by the preaching of <hi>Iohn</hi> Baptiſt,<note place="margin">Luk. 3.10.</note> euery one of them came vnto him, ſaying; <hi>What muſt we do:</hi> and of the Iayler who when once hee began to be humbled, came trembling and fell down be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas,</hi> ſaying;<note place="margin">Act. 18.29.30.</note> 
                  <hi>What muſt I doe to be ſaued.</hi> For howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer Gods ſeruants haue learned for the moſt part, what things in general muſt be done, yet ſtill they
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:7856:70"/> need to bee enformed in many things; therefore if wee truely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent vs of our ſinnes, the Lord wil neeuer leaue vs till all our iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties bee quite remoued from vs; for they that turne to the Lord by true repentance, the Lord will waſh them from all their ſinnes by the bloud of his Sonne; that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer offences we repent of, wee ſhal be ſure to haue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pardoned.</p>
               <p>Secondly, God accepteth of pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent perſons the wil for the deed as for the fulfilling of the law in abſolute perfection,<note place="margin">If we haue a willing mind to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme our duty, the Lord will accept the will for the deed.</note> that Chriſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone hath performed, he hath paid our debt, and cancelled the bond, and taken away the hand-writing that was againſt vs; now this one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly remaineth for vs, that we haue a good inclination, and a willing mind to performe our duty and labor to the vtmoſt of our ſtrength
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:7856:70"/> ſo to do, ſeeing and bewailing our manifold imperfections, errors, &amp; faylings, in euery one of our ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uices, which if wee can doe God will bee as well pleaſed with vs through his beloued ſonne, as if wee had kept the whole law, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any declining from it at al, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the right hand or to the left. That which is ſpoken in the matter of communicating vnto the neceſſities of the Saints in the Epiſtle to the Corinthians (to wit) if there be firſt a willing mind it is accepted according to that a man hath,<note place="margin">Cor 2.8.12.</note> &amp; not according to that he hath not, holdeth as true in all other ſeruices, that wee are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted with the Lord, according as we are inwardly affected, albeit our actions bee not anſwerable to our deſires: for hee that hath a ready minde to what hee can,
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:7856:71"/> and doth the ſame, would bee as ready to doe a great deale more, if his ability did ſerue; and therefore the Lord will ſhew his gracious acceptance of that which is done by him, though it be neuer ſo little as well as if it had beene a matter of a farre greater worth.</p>
               <p>Now that the true purpoſe and intent of the heart, is that which God principally regardeth in his ſeruants, is plainly proued out of holy Scripture; for we may reade in <hi>Geneſis</hi> what God ſaith of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,<note place="margin">Gen. 22.7.</note> By my ſelfe haue I ſworne</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>becauſe thou haſt done this thing, and not ſpared thine only ſon, therefore I will ſurely bleſſe thee:</hi> and yet <hi>Iſaac</hi> was not ſlaine, but <hi>Abraham</hi> withdrew his hand from him and ſpared him: yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee was content to kill him, and made all things ready for the
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:7856:71"/> ſacrificing of him, God accounts it as good, and rewardeth it as wel as if he had killed him indeed.</p>
               <p>So <hi>Dauid</hi> had but a purpoſe to build the temple,<note place="margin">1. Chron. 17 1. 1. Kin. 8.16.</note> which worke was afterward layd vpon <hi>Salomon,</hi> and by him performed, yet the Lord giueth him a good teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and large reward for his readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe that way: hee was content to ſpare him becauſe he had beene at great paines before in ſhedding the bloud of many enemies of the Church, and ſome remained yet ſtill to be ſubdued by him, yet this he telleth him for his comfort: <hi>whereas it was in thine heart to build an houſe vnto my name,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Chro. 17.10.11.12.</note> 
                  <hi>thou diddeſt well that thou wert ſo minded:</hi> and beſides this, he biddeth <hi>Nathan</hi> to carry him this meſſage; that the Lord would build him an houſe, and would raiſe vp ſeed after him,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:7856:72"/> and employ his ſonne in that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable ſeruice of building an houſe vnto the name of the Lord, and that hee would eſtabliſh his throne for euer: and therefore if we can beleeue that hee is pleaſed with our good actions, we may as well bee perſwaded that hee is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted with good our motions, and holy deſires that are ſtirred vp in our hearts by his owne ſpirit.</p>
               <p>And the reaſon why God ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth ſuch ſmall things in good worth is,<note place="margin">Pſal. 103.13</note> becauſe hee is both in name and nature a father;<note place="margin">Mal. 3.17.</note> yea, an heauenly father, and therfore hath compaſſion of thoſe that feare him: now hee that is a moſt merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and wiſe, and louing father, (as thoſe will be moſt mercifull to others, that haue taſted moſt of Gods mercy to themſelues) when he ſeeth that his child doth
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:7856:72"/> as well as he can, though it be but ſimply and poorely, yet hee will ſhew his liking of it, &amp; commend him for it: and ſo will God deale with vs, though wee cannot doe things perfitly, yet if we doe them obediently, hee will ſhew his loue and approbation of vs, and of our workes. When a little child doth cheerefully ayme and ſhoot at the marke which his father propoſeth vnto him, though by reaſon of his weakneſſe he ſhoot very wide and ſhort, yet it is well accepted of his father, as if hee did hit the white: and the like fatherly dealing ſhall we finde in God, that if wee bee faithfull in a little hee will eſteeme of vs as if wee performed a great deale more.<note place="margin">The perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of a Chriſtian here in this life.</note> Indeed when we haue put off the image of the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> and haue put on the image of the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> and haue changed
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:7856:73"/> the earth for heauen: then we ſhall not only obey truely, but perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; but here it is in truth, and ſo it muſt bee eſteemed, one degree of perfection is to ſee our owne im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections; and that was in <hi>Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah,</hi> and in thoſe of his time; <hi>O Lord I beſeech thee,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Nehe. 1.11</note> 
                  <hi>let thine eare now hearken to the prayer of thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, and to the prayer of thy ſeruants who deſire to feare thy name:</hi> hee could not ſay that they did ſo feare his name as they ſhould, but this they could ſay, that they deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to doe it better, which deſire was a fruite of the grace it ſelfe. This ſhould encourage vs ſtill to be doing in the ſeruices &amp; workes of God. But here ſome may ſay, we finde many imperfections, and many wants and weakeneſſes in our ſelues: be it ſo; yet if we ayme at perfection, and haue reſpect to euery commandement of God, &amp;
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:7856:73"/> come as neere to the marke as we can, the Lord wil accept vs accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that wee haue, and not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect vs for that we haue not; if wee could obey perfectly, to what end were Chriſt his obedience, and if God ſhould looke after none but thoſe that can fully pleaſe him in all things, he ſhould bee a Lord &amp; a maiſter without ſubiectes and ſeruants, <hi>If thou O Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 130.3.</note> 
                  <hi>ſaith Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid, ſhould marke what is done amiſſe who ſhould ſtand.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore though wee cannot pray with that feeling,<note place="margin">Our infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities ſhould not hinder vs, if we haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry comman<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dement.</note> heare and reade with that profit, ſing Pſalms with that ioyfulneſſe and cheere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes of heart as we ſhould, thogh wee cannot forgiue our enemies, long for Chriſt his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming, haue ſuch a tender feeling of the afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of the Saints, nor attaine to ſuch heauenly meditations night
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:7856:74"/> or day, as we doe deſire, and as God doth command, yet let vs not be diſcouraged if wee ſtriue to bring our wicked fleſh to the performance of thoſe du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: and though wee haue much adoe with it, yet if wee draw it as a Beare to the ſtake vnto Gods worſhip, and to the performance of good dueties in publicke and and priuate,<note place="margin">Rom. 7.12.</note> and when wee feele moſt backwardneſſe and vnto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſſe in our nature, yet wee conſent in our very ſoules, that the law of God is holy, iuſt and good, and that our willes and affections are indeed very corrupt and rebellious; but we would ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then all the world that things were otherwiſe wiſe with vs, that ſinne might be ſubdued, and grace planted in ſtead thereof, and it is our continuall griefe that God ſhould be ſo gracious, and kind, &amp;
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:7856:74"/> liberall to vs, and wee can bee no more obedient and loyall, and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiceable vnto him? if (I ſay) we find ſuch a heart within vs, we, need not to be diſmayed, but may cheerful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly go on with full perſwaſion and vndoubted reſolution that the Lord will be mercifull vnto vs, &amp; take our obedience in good worth if wee endeuour ſtill to be better, and to do better euery day then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, neuer ſtanding vpon that wee haue done,<note place="margin">The ſigne of a true heart.</note> but preſſing hard to the marke. This is an infallible note that wee are true hearted, he that feeleth but a little faith, a little loue, a little repentance, &amp;c. And would with all his heart haue them increaſed, theſe very deſires to obay, are euident ſignes that wee haue part in the Commandements. But here ſome may obiect and ſay, God
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:7856:75"/> requireth abſolute perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the Law; I anſwer, but not ſo in the Goſpel, but qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifieth the rigour of the Law by the ſatisfaction of a Mediator, and in our ſtead accepteth the true indeauour for the deede, and the good will for the worke it ſelfe: the law commandeth workes and perfect obedience, doe this and thou ſhalt liue: the Goſpell com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth faith. <hi>This is the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement that wee beleeue in the name of Ieſus Chriſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn 3.23.</note> 
                  <hi>and loue one another as he gaue commandement.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, that wee may there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore arme our ſelues with the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plete harneſſe of God to vanquiſh Satan,<note place="margin">Let euery one there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore arme himſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations.</note> and quench all his fierie darts: true it is in part, wee were the children of wrath by nature, but by grace we are not ſo; wee are not now vnder the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:7856:75"/> of nature, but vnder the ſtate of grace, and therefore no repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates but members of Chriſt,<note place="margin">It is the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God that can aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure vs that we are hls children.</note> and heires of ſaluation: Satan cannot tell who be reprobates, he is one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly an accuſer, but no iudge in this caſe, he is a lying ſpirit, but the ſpirit of God which cannot lye, aſſures vs that wee are the children of God: God hath giuen vs a Law to keepe which wee cannot keepe, yet his law is performed of vs euen to the full, though not of our perſons, yet in the perſon of Chriſt Ieſus; and though wee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not fulfill the law of workes, yet we can (by Gods inſpiring and aſſiſting grace) performe the law of faith which ſuffiſeth to ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Chriſt is not onely a iudge to condemne, but alſo a Sauiour to pardon; as hee hath iudgement ſo he hath mercy, but his mercy
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:7856:76"/> is aboue his iudgement, for it is aboue all his workes: our ſinnes are infinite, but Chriſt his mercy is more infinite to them that are in him, but wee are in him, and <hi>there is no condemnation to them which are in Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> We ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not ſinne ſo much as hee can pardon,<note place="margin">It is no pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption to hope for mercy, but the aſſura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of faith.</note> neither doe we ſinne with an high hand, but vpon infirmities: we are onely captiues, but not ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants to ſinnes; that is, we ſerue the law of ſinne whether wee will or no, but wee doe not willingly ſubmit our ſelues, vnto it nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is it preſumption in vs to hope for mercy, but it is faith: for God ſtands not ſo much vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the quantity as vpon the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of our faith, ſo as wee haue any at all, not the perfection but the truth of it, though it bee mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with infidelity or vnbeliefe.
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:7856:76"/> we ſay with the father of the child, which had a dumbe ſpirit, I <hi>beleeue Lord,</hi> but helpe my vnbeliefe.<note place="margin">Mat. 9.24.</note> That this faith of ours is no phantaſie or illuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or flattery of our ſelues, but a certaine aſſurance of Gods ſpirit, wee perſwade our ſelues by theſe reaſons; we hate our ſelues becauſe of our ſinne, we purpoſe to ſin ſo no more, wee call to GOD to ſtrenghen vs in this godly reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, we delight in the Law of God we loue all that feare him, we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the furtherance of the Goſpel,<note place="margin">Rom. 7.22.</note> and building vp the Kingdome of grace: We deſire to be diſſolued, and to be with Chriſt, that ſinne may ceaſe in vs, and this deſire of faith, and the groaning for want of any grace belonging to ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is the grace it ſelfe, and to ſuch a deſire a bleſſing is annexed. <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed are they which hunger and thirſt
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:7856:77"/> after righteouſneſſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 5.6.</note> 
                  <hi>for they ſhall be ſatisfied,</hi> euen at the full though not in this life, yet in the life to come.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, as we feele the diſeaſe, ſo wee muſt alſo feele the ſtrength of the medicine.<note place="margin">Rom. 7.23.</note> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> feeleth a Law in his members, &amp;c. which is the rebellion of concupiſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, and luſt in the fleſh by origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſinne:<note place="margin">2. Cor. 12.19.</note> So alſo, the grace of God by Ieſus Chriſt, ſhall deliuer him from it: our Sauiour ſaid to him in his greateſt temptations, <hi>My grace is ſufficient to ſtrengthen thee againſh all:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 14.31.</note> He held Saint <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> that hee could not ſinke, and prayed for him that his faith ſhould not faile him: Satan and our ſinnes are as the great army of the <hi>Aſſyrians,</hi> againſt <hi>Eliſeus,</hi> they appeared terrible, but on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide ſtood an army of Gods
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:7856:77"/> Angels, to fight for him:<note place="margin">2. Kin. 6.17.</note> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſtill wee muſt looke to the helps of grace; in all theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicts we ouercome by the helpe of him that loued vs.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.37. Phil, 4.13. Eſay 41.10.</note> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, he could doe all things. God ſaith by the Prophet, <hi>Be not afraid, for I am with thee, ſtep not aſide, for</hi> I <hi>thy God haue ſtrengthned thee, and haue asſiſted thee, the right hand of my iuſt man hath taken thy defence, and if God be with vs,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 8.31.</note> 
                  <hi>who can be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And that euery one of vs may be ſtirred vp to the performance of theſe duties:<note place="margin">This ſhould exhort eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one to get part in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note> let vs remember when God had made the heauens and the earth, he placed men and Angels in the ſame as his tennants to bring him in the rent of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in keeping the Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, therefore euery one of vs muſt bring in ſome thing to the
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:7856:78"/> Lords Exchequer, for the which the Lord may remember him. When <hi>Abraham</hi> went to ſacrifice <hi>Iſaac</hi> vpon Mount <hi>Moriah,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 22.2. Heb. 11.22.</note> when <hi>Moſes</hi> forſooke the pompe of <hi>Pharohs</hi> Court, to ſuſtaine afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions with Gods people,<note place="margin">1. King. 18.4.</note> when <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>badiah</hi> hid and relieued the Lords Prophets:<note place="margin">Iob. 31.20.</note> When <hi>Iob</hi> cauſed the loynes of the poore to bleſſe him, when <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> waſhed our Sauiours feete,<note place="margin">Luke 7.38.</note> and wiped them with the haires of her head, euery one of theſe had wherof the Lord might remember him:<note place="margin">Here we ſee that thoſe who warme the loynes of the poore and are an eye to the blind, haue that for which the Lord might remember them.</note> 
                  <hi>Therefore let your light ſo ſhine before men, that they ſeeing your good workes may glorifie your Father which is in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</hi> Here wee ſee the men for whom our heauenly Father is glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified, are ſuch whoſe workes ſhine afore men, who warme the loynes of the poore, and with
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:7856:78"/> their knowledge are an eye to the blind. I can hardly beleeue that God euer made any creature only to behold their glorious outſides; neither Starre, Pearle, Flower, or fethered Fowle, but to haue influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, vertues &amp; qualities benefici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al to mankind: much leſſe a man to know onely, or an Art onely to to be knowne, but all to his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and mans ſeruice; which to ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, is all the glory of man to keep the Commandements.<note place="margin">Pure religi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on is ſeene not in affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted words, but in the effect of charitable workes.</note> Who commends a Schoolemaſter whoſe Schollers can ſay and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand their Rules, but ſpeake not and write not any good ſtiles by them: A Captaine, whoſe Souldiers can skill of millitary termes and orders, vnleſſe their acts and exploits of warre be ſuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Who prayſeth a Courſer that feedes well, or pranceth
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:7856:79"/> proudly, but is not deedy for the race, or trauell, ſpeede or length. Little ſayes the Scripture of the learning of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, but much of their acts, theſe are the richeſt, and vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſtiles of commendation in Scripture.<note place="margin">Num. 14.19.20. Acts 10.2.</note> 
                  <hi>Moſes,</hi> a man mighty in words and deedes. <hi>Cornelius,</hi> a man fearing God, and giuing much Almes. The Centurion wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of fauour, for he hath built vs a Synagogue.<note place="margin">Acts 9, 39.</note> 
                  <hi>Dorcas</hi> made thus many coates for the poore, &amp;c. Such benefactors their workes ſhall follow them and praiſe them in the gates heere, yea, and at the great Day obtaine that, <hi>Come ye bleſſed of my Father, for I was naked, and you cloathed mee,</hi> I <hi>was hungry, and you fed me,</hi> for ſuch men God is bleſſed of men, and ſuch men ſhall be bleſſed of God
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:7856:79"/> in their deedes: and as the more knowing without doing, ſhall procure the more ſtripes, ſo the more doing with knowing, ſhall haue double honour, becauſe God was double honoured in them:<note place="margin">Reu. 22.12.</note> 
                  <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold,</hi> I <hi>come quickly, and my reward is in my hand, to giue euery man ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his deedes:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reu. 22.14.</note> 
                  <hi>Bleſſed are they that keepe my Cammande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments:</hi> If you know them, and do them not, miſerable are you, but theſe things if you know and doe them, you are the happieſt men li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing.</p>
               <p>Of all men I hold them moſt wretched and ſelfe-condemned,<note place="margin">Here are all thoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, who intend not to bee dooers of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as well as hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers.</note> that bend their ſtudies to diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, not tending to be dooers, as well as Students and Preachers; not much wiſer are ſuch as will be preciſe Profeſſors of Religion, but not Practiſioners. Oh that heere
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:7856:80"/> were not too many ſuch to bee found in theſe dayes. They may fitly be reſembled to ſuch as plow and ſowe all the yeare, and neuer reape, to the Graſhopper that ſings all the Summer, and wants in the Winter, to women euer conceiuing, and neuer comming to the birth: and beſt of all, to that of Chriſt, comparing ſome hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers vnto fooles that build on the ſand of bare hearing and profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing,<note place="margin">Mat. 7.26, 27.</note> who thinke that all Religion conſiſteth in hearing Sermons, neglecting the performance, but the wiſe are they that build on the rock of doing, vnſhakeable. Search all the Scripture, and ſee if any couenants or grants were made to hearing or knowing, and not all to dooing the Commandements: is not the ancient tenour of the law; doe this, and liue: and the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell,
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:7856:80"/> repent belieue, &amp; liue,<note place="margin">Mat. 12.50.</note> which implying ſundry conſequences and fruits of it. <hi>He that doth my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers will, he is my brother and ſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, not euery one that ſaith, Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 7.21.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord, but he that doth my fathers wil; to him that doth ill, ſhall bee tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and anguiſh to euery ſoule of Iew and Grecian,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 2.8.9, 10.</note> 
                  <hi>to him that doth well, ſhall be honour and and peace to all the Iſrael of God.</hi> Vnto whom ſhall that <hi>Euge</hi> bee giuen at that great day, but to the dooer? and in what forme, but <hi>well done, thou good ſeruant, that haſt not buried thy Talent in a Napkin;</hi> he himſelfe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth the manner. <hi>Behold,</hi> I <hi>come quickly, my reward is in my hand, to giue euery man according to his workes: Bleſſed is euery one that doth my Commandements, that he may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ate of the Tree of life; and enter tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ow the gates into the Citty:</hi> In all
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:7856:81"/> which happines in this life, &amp; that to come is confirmed vpon the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing acts and exerciſes, not vpon the dead habits of any grace what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer: In all labour there is abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance; but in the conceits of the braine, and talke of the lips, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but emptineſſe and miſery.</p>
               <p>Next to Gods glory and a mans owne good, a Chriſtian placeth much happineſſe in winning and edifying others,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 12.10.</note> to which purpoſe a ſpeechles life hath more life in it then aliue ſpeech. So <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> commends a good life, aboue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>farre profeſſion: For <hi>it is able,</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>to confute and conuert Pagans;</hi> withall he tels vs, <hi>they haue a louder language then the ſunne and Moone, whoſe ſound yet goes ouer all the world, publiſhing Gods glory:</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaith Chriſt to his Diſciples, <hi>goe and tell,</hi> not what you haue
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:7856:81"/> heard me preach, but ſaw me doe. <hi>How the blind receiue ſight, &amp;c. If I doe not ſuch workes as none other hath done before me,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The beſt courſe for vs to take to winne o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, is to be doers of that wee profeſſe.</note> I deſire not men to belieue in me. By theſe courſes <hi>Peter</hi> would haue Chriſtians win their neighbours, and wiues their husbands, rather the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by tutering of them: then would neighbours fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low one another to the right Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and true Church, as Tradſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do to thoſe markets where they ſee them gather wealth faſteſt; yea imitate their liues, and bring forth fruits as <hi>Iacobs</hi> ſheepe, if they ſaw their rods ſpeckled with works, as well as with words: thus ſaint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtines</hi> famous mother, taught one of her neighbour Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, complaining of her churliſh <hi>Nabal,</hi> &amp; wondring how ſhe won her peruerſe husband, why ſayes ſhe, <hi>I obſerued his mind, and pleaſed
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:7856:82"/> him in all indifferent things, forbore him in his paſſions, gaue him all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent in dyet, and attendance, and ſo haue made him firſt Gods, and then mine by degrees.</hi> Theſe are the Arts and charmes, that if they were now vſed by one Chriſtian to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, would couer multitudes of ſins, and conuert multitudes of ſinners. Theſe things mind and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe, theſe things if you know and doe, you ſhall ſaue your ſelues and thoſe you liue withall, and ſo be euery way bleſſed men.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The doers of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are only bleſſed</note>Thus wee ſee, that doing the Commandements only, brings in the bleſſednes without which all our knowing makes and leaues vs, but diſhonorable to God, vncom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable to our ſelues, ſcandalous to others; in no neerer keeping the Commandements, then <hi>Balaam, Iudas,</hi> and the diuell himſelfe, who
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:7856:82"/> the more they know, the worſe for them, the more ſinne, and the more puniſhment. If knowing made vp bleſſednes, England were an happy Nation, out times as happy as euer any, but if doing be required, great is the felicity of both queſtionleſſe: <hi>the more any man knowes or profeſſes to know, and the leſſe they doe, the more they doe diſhonor God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And what are ſuch themſelues the better for their knowledge:<note place="margin">They which know them &amp; do them not, they do increaſe their ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row.</note> but as the Preacher ſpeaketh in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother ſence. <hi>Hee that encreaſeth ſuch knowledge, addeth ſorrow.</hi> What a miſery is it for a man to haue no inward faithfull know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge or affection to the Goſpell, nor better proofe of his loue thereto, then that hee carried it alwayes about him, at his Girdle.
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:7856:83"/> My meaning is not to taxe Bible carrying, &amp; Chriſtian conference which I hold a better grace then Bootes, Spurres and Rapiers, on Sundayes, or Fannes of Fethers, &amp; top-gallant Enſignes of vanity euery day, but only to ſhew the foppery of them that carry Gods word and law, not in their hearts but only in their heads, or in their memories or vnderſtandings. Let theſe bee as wiſe as they may in their own conceits, to me they are no better then Aſſes which carry dainty burdens, but taſte not of them, <hi>Verily a man knowes no more rightly then he Practiſes:</hi> it is ſaid of Chriſt, hee knew no ſinne, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he did no ſinne, and in that ſence, hee knowes no good that doth no good. Hee that will obey, ſhall know my Fathers will, and ſuch as will
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:7856:83"/> not doe what they know to bee good,<note place="margin">The abuſe of that wee know will be the chiefe cauſe to depriue vs of it.</note> ſhall ſoone vnknow that which they know, it being iuſt with God to puniſh ſhipwrack of a good conſcience, with the fraught of knowledge, according to that imprecation in the Epiſtle to the Hebrewes, that if they ſhould abuſe their skill in mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke, their right hand might forget his cunning, and their tongue cleaue to the roofe of their mouth, from which iuſt Iudgement it comes to paſſe, that many become colder in matters of Religion, and kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the Commandents: For, <hi>a good vnderſtanding haue all they that doe thereafter, and curſed are all ſuch as know theſe things, and doe the cleane contrary:</hi> Curſed, I ſay are they becauſe they not onely caſt away themſelues, but alſo
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:7856:84"/> lay a ſtumbling block before o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, both weake ones within, and bad ones without, ſuch as theſe know God, and yet deny him in their liues, and are repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates to euery good worke; ſuch as buy by one Ballance, and ſell by another, haue a forme of knowledge, which they pretend in themſelues, &amp; preſcribe to others, with all ſeuere ſeuerity, and liue themſelues in ſecret by contrary rules. Friends in ſhew, but indeed <hi>Enemies to the Croſſe of Chriſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 3.18.</note> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane beaſts, for all the chewing of the Cud, which makes men miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, not only their perſons, but the very religion which they profeſſe in the higheſt ſtreine of ſtrickt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. I wonder with what face ſuch can call themſelues Chriſtians, or vvith vvhat eares can heare themſelues ſo
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:7856:84"/> called; doth any man looke to bee accounted a Carpenter, that cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth himſelfe ſo, but neuer ſquares timber, nor erected frames; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to all hearers and goers to Sermons I ſay, play not the fools as moſt doe, heare not to heare, goe not to Church as many now adayes do, for faſhio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſake or to get an opinion of zeale, or as boyes go into the water to play and pad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle there onely, not to waſh and be cleane.</p>
               <p>Therefore let vs all that lay clayme to that honourable name,<note place="margin">Let vs ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doe the workes of Chriſtians and ſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue our ſelues.</note> doe the workes of Chriſtians and thereby approue your ſelues to God and man, as the Angell to <hi>Manoch</hi> who being asked of his name, made anſwer, <hi>It was wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and did wonderfully aſcend in the flame,</hi> and made good his name by his action. The art of doing is
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:7856:85"/> that which requires ſtudy, ſtrength and diuine aſſiſtance: do the ſinnes that ſwarm in our times, proceed from ignorance, or incontinence rather, and wilfulnes? It were hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py if men had that plea; if the light were not ſo great, the times &amp; the nations had not ſinne, who amongſt vs is ſo ignorant but hee knowes that Idolatry, ſwearing, ſtabbing, whoring, and exceſſiue drinking are ſinnes, and that for theſe things comes the anger of God? Is any ſo ſimple that hee knowes not the ten Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and the ſum of the Goſpel yet how deſperately doe men ruſh on the pikes, careleſly, &amp; wittingly willingly, ſeeing the gulfe, and yet leaping into it. Vpon this there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doe I wiſh Chriſtians would ſet prices, and ſpend their ſtudies, euen about the art of doing the
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:7856:85"/> Conmandements. But here ſome may aske, how ſhall wee attaine this facility and faculty of doing? I anſwer, to wiſh it,<note place="margin">Good de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires is the beſt halfe, eſpecially when it breeds prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er for the dead.</note> and heartily to deſire it is halfe, yea and the beſt halfe of the worke, for a man or woman, to effect goodneſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue cunning is a good ſigne, and a good helpe and ſtep to bee ſuch an one, eſpecially when this deſire breeds prayer for power to doe, knowing that <hi>without Chriſt wee can doe iuſt nothing:</hi> therefore let euery one of vs do that we ſhould do, and bleſſed are we. If we know that <hi>Baal</hi> be God, if Rome be the true Church, let vs turne to it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine; if wee know that ſwearing, dicing, ſwaggering, and fooliſh faſhion following be good things; let vs all fall to doe thoſe things: but if God hath giuen vs the truth and the light, let vs walke in it, and
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:7856:86"/> worke by it while it is to day, leſt if we play reuell and riot, by it the Candleſticke be remoued, and the light put out: if purity, ſanctitie, and ſobrietie, be knowne to vs to be good things, and pleaſing to God to keepe the Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and delight therein, O hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py then, thriſe bleſſed are we if we doe them.</p>
               <p>Therefore to conclude, though I confeſſe my ſelfe vnworthy to write,<note place="margin">The conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of that man, that delighteth in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts ſhuld moue vs to get our part therein.</note> yet I beſeech you let my counſell be acceptable to the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; that is, let euery one of vs get ſome part in the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements, for the which the Lord may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member vs, and the remembrance whereof may bee a comfort to vs at the houre of death, let vs pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide with <hi>Ioſeph</hi> in the time of plenty againſt the day of ſcarcity,<note place="margin">. Iohn. 92</note> 
                  <hi>the night commeth when no man can
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:7856:86"/> worke:</hi> God loues a liuing ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and a chearfull giuer: therfore <hi>let vs thinke with Titus Veſpaſian wee haue loſt thay day wherein wee haue not done ſome good.</hi> O what a bleſſed houre ſhall that be, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in our ſoules ſhall expire with <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekias</hi> words:<note place="margin">Eſa. 38.3.</note> 
                  <hi>I beſeech thee O Lord remember how I haue walked before thee in truth, and with a perfect heart and haue done that which is good in thy ſight.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iud. 5.21.</note> Then may wee ſay with <hi>Deborah, O my ſoule thou haſt mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched valiantly.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 116.7.</note> Yea then may wee ſay with <hi>Dauid; Return vnto thy reſt O my ſoule, for the Lord hath rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded thee.</hi> Death is the worlds ſtrict doore keeper, and will ſee,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 6.7.</note> that as wee brought nothing into the world, ſo we ſhall carry foorth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing againe: yet can he not hinder vs from that bleſſedneſſe which the Oracle of heauen hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:7856:87"/> to all thoſe that delight in the Commandements: <hi>Bleſſed are the dead which die in the Lord, they reſt from their labours, and their works follow them.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reu. 14.13.</note> Let vs conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that onely our good workes will be our companions to heauen they ſhall bee our honour in life, our comfort in death, and our crowne at the laſt reſurrection: beſeeching him to enable vs with grace for the performance of all thy Commandements, for thy truth, and for thy names ſake, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="verse">
               <epigraph>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>VERSE 2.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <q>His ſeed ſhall bee mighty vpon earth, the generation of the righteous ſhall be bleſſed.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>HAuing ſpoken of the bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of that man that feareth the Lord, and delighteth in his
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:7856:87"/> Commandements. Now in this Verſe the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> ſheweth the happy ſucceſſe of this bleſſed man; <hi>His ſeed ſhall bee mighty vpon earth, &amp;c.</hi> That is, they ſhall not onely haue ſpirituall grace, but alſo right vnto, and the right vſe of all the benefites of this life:<note place="margin">True obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence bring outward proſperity.</note> for <hi>true obedience to Gods Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, though it bee not perfect, brings the bleſsing of God vpon vs for outwards things, as well as for inward.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is promiſed in <hi>Deuterono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie,</hi> where <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpeaketh thus vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the people of Iſrael:<note place="margin">Deu. 28.2. &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>If thou ſhalt obey diligently the voyce of the Lord thy God, and obſerue and doe all his Commandements, which I command thee this day, then the Lord thy God will ſet thee on high aboue all the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the earth, and all thoſe bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings ſhall come to thee, &amp;c. Belſſed ſhalt
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:7856:88"/> thou be in the citie, and bleſſed alſo in the field,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Cor. 9.7.</note> &amp;c. Shewing that true and faithfull obedience is that which bringeth all manner of bleſſings for body and ſoule, for name and eſtate; yea, and for ſeed and poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie alſo: and therefore the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle telleth <hi>Timothy,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Tim. 6.5.</note> that <hi>godlineſſe is great gaine, and</hi> that it <hi>hath the promiſes of this life, and of the life to come.</hi> In which regard <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith, <hi>I haue beene yong, and now am old, yet haue I not ſeene the righteous for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſal. 4 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 25.</note> 
                  <hi>nor his ſeed begging bread:</hi> therfore <hi>Dauids ſpeech</hi> is well to be obſerued; for he doth not ſay, the righteous is neuer forſaken,<note place="margin">How to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand Dauids wordes.</note> but I neuer ſaw it; ſpeaking there of his own experience and obſeruation: hee had ſeene (and ſo may wee) that children of great men haue broken foorth into many horrible ſinnes, and ſo haue beene brought
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:7856:88"/> to a ſtrange and miſerable and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent death, &amp; many wofull ſtraits &amp; extremities before their death: but he neuer ſaw, neither ſhall wee ſee, the godly ſeed of godly men forſaken, of God and men, and left as vagabonds to beg their bread, but God hath euer had (and ſtill will haue) a ſpeciall care of them, and euer made all neceſſary prouiſion for them, either hee himſelfe by a more particular pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence of his, caſteth ſufficency of theſe outward things vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or bleſſeth their labours, ſo that they are made a meanes of main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance vnto them, or if they fayle that way, hee mooueth the hearts of ſome other of his ſeruants to pittie them, and to ſupply their wants, ſo that whatſoeuer their neceſſities bee, they are freede from that curſe
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:7856:89"/> that is denounced againſt the ſeed of the wicked, to wit, that they ſhould wander vp and downe as vagrants, begging their bread, and making a trade of that vile wretched courſe of life.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Nothing that is need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſhall be wanting, when Gods fauour is not.</note>Teaching vs this much, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that is needful ſhall be wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to thoſe that are in the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of the Lord, ſuch as haue his fauour ſhall haue all good bleſſings flowing to them, and following of them. <hi>Dauid</hi> doth notably confirme this in many of his Pſalmes, as in the three and twentieth Pſalme where profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing God to bee his ſhepheard, maketh this inference therupon: <hi>Therefore I ſhall not want,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 23.1.6.</note> but doubtleſſe, <hi>kindeneſſe, and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie ſhall follow mee all the dayes of my life;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſa. 34 9.10</note> and againe, <hi>the Lyons doe lacke and ſuffer hunger, but
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:7856:89"/> they which ſeeke the Lord ſhall want nothing that is good:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 84.11.</note> alſo <hi>Dauid</hi> ſayth, <hi>the Lord God is a ſunne and a ſhield vnto vs, the Lord will giue grace and glory, and no good thing will hee with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold from them that walke vpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</hi> And is not this the bleſſing that is promiſed to ſuch as feare the Lord, that all good things ſhould flow vnto them from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earth, that they ſhall be hleſſed in the houſe, in the field, in their basket, in their ſtore, in the fruite of their bodyes, in the encreaſe of their cattle and in the aboundance of all things,<note place="margin">Let no man doubt of this truth, for God is the Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen &amp; earth and the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>oſer of all things.</note> thus wee ſee, that where Gods fauour is there is want of nothing that is needfull. And there is cauſe why we ſhuld reſt fully reſolued of this point, that none of Gods houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold ſhall euer want neceſſary re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe,
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:7856:90"/> becauſe all will yeeld that God is the Gouernour of heauen and earth, and the diſpoſer of all things in them both, and then they muſt grant further, that thoſe that are beſt, and doe beſt, ſhall ſpeede beſt, becauſe God loueth them moſt; and how then can we make queſtion whether or no, the Lord will beſtow vpon them a compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent meaſure, and a comfortable vſe of theſe earthly bleſſings, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all is in his hand, and he wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſo well vnto his owne peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; eſpecially ſeeing hee hath ſtraightly charged vs, not to care what wee ſhall eate or drinke,<note place="margin">Mat. 6.25.</note> or what wee ſhall put on, but <hi>firſt to ſeeke the kingdome of God and his righteouſneſſe,</hi> promiſing vs faithfully, that if wee doe ſo all other things ſhall be caſt vpon vs.</p>
               <p>And as he hath promiſed this,
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:7856:90"/> ſo hath hee from time to time per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed it,<note place="margin">If we will proſper in our outward eſtate, wee muſt thriue in pietie.</note> as wee may obſerue throughout the booke of Iudges, of <hi>Samuel,</hi> and of the Chroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, for there it is to be ſeene, that when godlineſſe proſpered in the ſoules of Gods people, they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpered their outward eſtate, &amp; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſinne (on the other ſide) had made hauocke in their ſoules, then the <hi>Madianites,</hi> and the <hi>Philiſtims</hi> and other enemies, made ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocke in their countrey, when they and their kings thriued in pietie, and did grow in the knowledge of God and zeale of his glory, then it went well with them for outward plenty and aboundance, but when I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry and impietie, beganne once to thriue in their hearts, and in their land, they neuer had long nor ſettled proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:7856:91"/> but their enemies hands and ſwords preuayled againſt them, for taking away of their liues, and the ruinating of their eſtates.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Sinful cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer proſper.</note>Firſt, here is matter of terrour for all wicked worldlings that thinke to aduantage and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance themſelues by ſinnefull and and naughty courſes, that is an ill way to riſe, for <hi>the riches of iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſhall not proſper,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 10.2. Iere. 22.23.24.</note> though they build their houſes neuer ſo high, and aduance their neſts vnto the ſtarres, yet the Lords hand ſhall pull them thence, and caſt them downe into the very duſt: they thinke their houſes, their names, and their ſubſtance ſhall remayne for euer, and that they ſhall make themſelues and theirs, by ioyning houſe to houſe, and land to land, by oppreſſing the
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:7856:91"/> poore and needy, and by defrau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the fatherleſſe and widow, and ſuch as cannot right them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues; but alas, they little conſider in the meane while, that God is the Iudge of the world, and that hee will reward euery man accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his workes; they imagine their eſtate ſhall be according to their wealth, and ſo it might bee indeede, if God were not the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour of the world, but ſith he is ſo, it ſhall goe with euery one according to that he is, and not according to that hee hath: and therefore as God would haue it proclaimed to the godly,<note place="margin">Iſa. 3.10.</note> 
                  <hi>ſay yee, ſurely it ſhall goe well with the iuſt, for they ſhall eate the fruite of their workes:</hi> ſo he would haue this denounced againſt the vngodly, <hi>Wo be to the wicked, it ſhall bee euill with him for the reward of his hands
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:7856:92"/> ſhall bee giuen him,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſa. 3.11.</note> 
                  <hi>they ſhall reape that which they haue ſowed.</hi> It were and abſurd thing for one that hath ſowne nothing but cockle and fitches to exſpect a good crop of wheat, and as contrary to all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is it for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſowe iniquity to think they ſhall reape any thing but affliction, they may delude themſelues with vaine hopes, but they ſhall neuer obtaine any hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe and proſperity from the Lord nay ſurely he hates both the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and their practiſes, and therefore they &amp; their wicked ſeed ſhall be rooted out, as wee may ſee it verified in many of the kings of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as in <hi>Ieroboam, Ahab Baa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſha, &amp;c.</hi> And moſt notably in that place of <hi>Ieremie,</hi> concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Iehoiakim</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Ioſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah, woe vnto him,</hi> ſayth the Lord,
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:7856:92"/> 
                  <hi>that buildeth his houſe by vnrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ier. 22.13.89.</note> 
                  <hi>and his Chambers without equity, hee vſeth his neighbour without wages, and giueth him not for his works, &amp;c. Shalt thou raigne becauſe thou cloſeſt thy ſelfe in Cedar? did not thy Father eate and drinke and proſper, when he executed Iudgement and Iuſtice? &amp;c.</hi> Where is declared in the example of <hi>Ioſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioſ. 11.23. No certaine way to proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in, but in the practiſe of godlines, for that bringeth all true honor and proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</note> the godly Father on the one ſide, that the true knowledge of God, and the practiſe of godlines and righteouſneſſe, bringeth all true honour and proſperity; and on the other ſide in the example of <hi>Iehoiakim,</hi> the wicked ſonne is ſhewed, that impiety ioyned with oppreſſion; and cruelty with fraud and deceit, and iniurious dealing, man liues a baſe and diſhonoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble life, and dyes a ſhamefull and Ignominious death, as wee ſee it
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:7856:93"/> many times comes to paſſe, that while he is in the World, he ſhall liue vndeſired, and when he goeth out of the World, he ſhall die vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamented.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The beſt way to thriue in all the world is, to get Religion into our hearts.</note>Therefore let this encourage men, if they would haue good things either in right or in poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, to labour to get Religion in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their hearts, and to be as much afraid of ſinne as of miſery, and as deſirous of grace, as they are of proſperity: which if we could do, we ſhould find Gods eyes open to conſider of vs, and his hand to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue vs continually in all our wants and neceſſities. And as wee ſhould bee thus carefull for our ſelues, ſo we ſhould be alſo for our children, there is no good parent but would wiſh his children might be prouided for, and liue in the World in good ſort, now heere
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:7856:93"/> is the way to purchaſe them a good eſtate in the earth, vſe the meanes to bring them vnto the feare of God, and to haue faith in God, for when the Lyons that are full of might, and rage and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty, doe lack and ſuffer hunger, then they that ſeeke the Lord ſhal want nothing that is good,<note place="margin">Pſal. 34.10</note> God will haue a care that his ſheepe ſhall haue conuenient paſture, and be in good liking, though the Lyons bee pined and hunger-ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and when ſtrong and mighty men are in miſery, want, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity,<note place="margin">Heq. 13.15.</note> yet then Gods poore and weake ſeruants ſhall haue that will ſatisfie and content them, for God hath ſaid, that he will neuer leaue them nor forſake them: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are they the moſt proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and wiſe Parents, that bring vp their children in the inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:7856:94"/> and information of the Lord, for ſuch ſhall poſſeſſe the earth, and <hi>the generation of the righteous ſhall be bleſſed.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 37.11.</note> Children are not alwayes the better for the goods of their Parents, but they are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes the better for their good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, for as we haue it heere, the generation of the righteous ſhall be bleſſed; it is more then if it had beene ſaid, they ſhall enioy honor, credit, wealth, and whatſoeuer outward bleſſing elſe can bee na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, for that implyeth thus much; that they ſhall haue the good gifts of God, ſo farre as they are need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for them, and that they ſhall haue the right vſe of them to their comfort.<note place="margin">Heere is great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation for Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, they ſhall not want ſome to relieue them.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, here is a ſingular com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort for Gods children that are in many wants &amp; neceſſities, ſo long as there is any godly man or wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:7856:94"/> that will doe any thing for Chriſt his ſake, for their owne comforts ſake, they ſhall not bee deſtitute of reliefe, for God hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded his ſeruants to ſuccour them, and hath made many graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous promiſes to ſuch as are merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, &amp; will beare the burdens of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and if men ſhould faile them, the Lord himſelfe will looke vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, who beholds their trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and ſees their teares, and is acquainted with all their griefes, and he that bids others to be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull, he will not be vnmercifull himſelfe, and therefore it is, that men doe deny vs helpe, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort many times, becauſe God would haue vs draw neerer vnto him, whoſe eyes are euer vpon vs, and whoſe eares are alwayes open to heare the cryes of the poore, &amp; of thoſe that are humbled before him.</p>
               <pb n="174" facs="tcp:7856:95"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The wicked flouriſh.</note>But heere ſome may obiect and ſay, that the wicked and prophane perſons liue in all manner of plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, when the godly ſuſtaine penu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and ſcarcity, and in appearance, godlineſſe is not the beſt courſe to procure a happy and proſperous eſtate: to this I anſwere, that how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer the wicked of the World ſeeme to thriue beſt, and to enioy great matters, in compariſon of that which good Chriſtians haue, yet in truth their caſe is nothing ſo good as is the caſe of Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, for though they be preſſed and pinched with many diſtreſſes and wants, and driuen to many extremities and ſtraights, yet they may be fuller of ioy in the middeſt of their aflictions, then the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed are in the middeſt of their iolli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,<note place="margin">Act. 16.25</note> 
                  <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> were fuller of gladnes, and of true contented<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:7856:95"/> in the Dungeon,<note place="margin">The childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God haue more ioy in the middeſt of their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the wicked haue in their grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt iollity.</note> when their feete were faſt in the Stocks, then <hi>Herod</hi> was on his Throne, hauing all flatterers about him, to extoll and magnifie him, the very teares of the people of God, are ſwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and more comfortable then the greateſt of carnall men can be, for <hi>the Lord is with his in mercy and goodneſſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 37.16.</note> where as his face is bent againſt the wicked and impudent, and thence it is, that <hi>a little that the righteous hath, is better then great riches of the vngodly: better is a dinner of greene herbes, ſeaſoned with the bleſſing of God, then many dainty diſhes poyſoned with Gods wrath and malediction.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">If the ſaints of God ſhould want outward things, yet they ſhall haue Gods fauour. Pſal. 84.11.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And albeit, the Saints of God be ſometimes depriued of theſe things, yet they ſhall neuer be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued of Gods fauour, and that want of outward things, ſhall bee
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:7856:96"/> ſupplied with inward graces, they haue a ſure promiſe, that they ſhal haue ſufficient, and God neuer gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth leſſe then he promiſeth, but many times he giueth more then we expect; and if that which is wanting in droſſe bee paid home in good gold, wee neede not to complaine, as if we were loſers by ſuch an exchange, therefore ſaith ſaith <hi>Salomon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prou. 2.20.21.22.</note> 
                  <hi>Walke thou in the way of good men, and keepe the wayes of the righteous, for the iuſt ſhall dwell in the Land, and the vpright men ſhall remaine in it, bue the wicked ſhall be cut off from the earth, and the tranſgreſſors ſhall be rooted out.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, this ſheweth vs a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betwixt the fauor of God, and the fauor of men, true it is, the fauour of Princes and of great men brings with it many priue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges and preferments, but they
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:7856:96"/> cannot aſſure vs if euery good thing, neither are they able to do all things that they would, yea many times they are preuented by ſudden death, before opportunity be offered to manifeſt their loue, and when they doe ſhew fauour vnto any, how vnſtable is it, and how vncertaine this <hi>Hammon</hi> found; to day hee is honoured,<note place="margin">Eſt. 71.10. There is great diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the fauour of God, and fauour of men.</note> to morrow hanged, but it is other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe with God, his fauour brings with it a ſupply of all things need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and they that rely vpon it ſhall neuer be deceiued nor diſappoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but may be aſſured of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>His ſeed ſhall bee mighty vpon earth.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The fauour of God is to be ſought aboue all things.</note> From hence we learne that Gods fauour doth make ſupply of all things needfull, let vs ſeeke then and labour for his fauour be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all things, for if this bee not wanting, no bleſſing ſhall be; this
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:7856:97"/> is the maine and mother bleſſing, ſo that if wee can obtaine it, wee ſhall obtaine all other bleſſings whatſoeuer, we ſee how farre men will goe, what labour and paines they will endure, and all for the fauour of a Prince,<note place="margin">Pſal. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>whoſe breath is in his Noſthrils, and whoſe thoughts periſh,</hi> and yet no King can be ſo bountifull to his fauouries, as is the God of Heauen: excellent things ſhall bee done to the man whom the King doth honour, but farre more excellent to him whom the Lord doth fauour: why then doe we no more reſpect his loue? why doe we not vſe the meanes to become gratious in his eyes? Oh let vs all ſeeke his fauour before the fauour of Princes, let vs ſeeke his face euermore.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, this teacheth vs to haue our conuerſation without
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:7856:97"/> couetouſnes, which is as inſatiable as the graue, in euery eſtate &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition learne to depend vpon the Lords prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, <hi>Commit thy way vnto the Lord, and truſt in him,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 37.5.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp; he ſhall bring it to paſſe.</hi> Vſe no vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full meanes, take not any indirect courſe for the obtaining of wealth or ſupplying our wants, for God hath engaged his promiſe and his truth, to ſee our needs ſupplied.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, let it comfort the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God in the middeſt of all the miſeries of this mortall life;<note place="margin">Nothing can make vs miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, where Gods fauor is not wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</note> for what can make vs miſerable, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we enioy the fauour of God, and the light of his countenance, which is the Fountaine of all good, and the ground of all other mercies whatſoeuer: what <hi>Elka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah</hi> ſaid to <hi>Hannah,</hi> complaining for want of children, may Gods fauour ſpeake to all that haue their
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:7856:98"/> parts in it, in euery diſtreſſe. Am not I vnto thee inſtead of riches, wealth, glory and greatneſſe in the world? ſurely yes, it is inſtead of theſe, and better then all theſe vnto vs; let therefore the inioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this ſerue for a ſupply for all our wants, of what kind ſoeuer; let vs make Gods fauour to bee that vnto vs which wee want, for he that can aſſure himſelfe of this, hath a ſufficient ſalue for eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſore.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">There is no certaine way to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance our ſelues, but true religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</note>
                  <hi>The generation of the righteous ſhall bee bleſſed.</hi> Hence we learne that Religion and true piety, is the ready way to the higheſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancement that can be, therefore let vs ſet our hearts chiefely there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, and aboue all the treaſures in the World, principally to ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect that: wee count it good huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry to ſeeke after thoſe things
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:7856:98"/> that will doe vs moſt good, if ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer bee offered, we will preferre it before braſſe; and if gold be offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, we will take it rather then ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. Now concerning this hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly wiſedome it is ſaid,<note place="margin">Pro. 8.10.11</note> 
                  <hi>Receiue mine inſtruction, and not ſiluer; and knowledge rather then fine gold; for wiſedome is better then precious ſtones, and all treaſures are not to bee compared vnto her.</hi> And this ſhould encourage vs rather to vſe all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry for the obtaining of this bleſſed eſtate, becauſe it is a thing haue-able: it were in vaine for a baſe perſon to ſue to bee a King, a Duke, or a Lord, none almoſt is ſo fooliſh as to ſeeke for ſuch pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferments, becauſe they know it would be but loſt labour, but there is not the meaneſt Seruant, Slaue, or Bondman, but may attaine to this ſpirituall dignity, which is far
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:7856:99"/> beyond all the aduancement that the Kingdomes of this world can poſſibly yeeld: hee that can pray, heare, meditate, confer, and with all good care and conſcionable reſpect, vſe all Gods ordinances for the obtaining of faith and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther graces, which doe euer ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company the ſame, ſhall be ſure of good and happy ſucceſſe; for <hi>the Lord will be found of thoſe that ſeeke him with a true heart,</hi> therefore let vs not ſo caſt our eyes on earthly commodities, as that in the meane time wee neglect this pearle of price, and this ineſtimable Iew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell, that will ſo exceedingly enrich vs:<note place="margin">2. Cor. 9.21</note> the Apoſtle telleth vs, that thoſe that runne in a raſe for a prize, though it bee but a Garland that is ſet vp, yet they will put off all that might clog &amp; hinder them in their race, but eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:7856:99"/> if they ſhould runne for a Crowne of gold, neither will they be ſo fooliſh to ſtoope downe to take vp euery pinne or poynt that lyeth in the way, and yet they run but at an vncertainety, when they haue done their beſt, another may carry away both the honour and commodity from them: from all which the Apoſtle would haue vs draw this concluſion, that if ſuch kind of perſons will ſo beſtirre themſelues, and ſeeke to acquit themſelues euery way like men, then much more ought we to put our ſelues to it, ſith wee runne not at an vncertainety,<note place="margin">Only the godly are ſure to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the Crowne.</note> but are ſure to obtaine the Crowne, one ſhall not preuent nor depriue another, but all ſhall vndoubtedly get that which they doe expect, and ſhall attaine vnto not a fading and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing, but an abiding and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:7856:100"/> dignity, they ſhall be bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: but here ſome may ſay, if wee beſtow our paines and endeauour ſo much about ſpirituall things, in the meane time wee ſhall neglect thoſe earthly things that are need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and ſo bring our ſelues to po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerty. I anſwere, not ſo, for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion of our euerlaſting eſtate doth neuer impaire our preſent e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate:<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4 8.</note> For <hi>Godlineſſe hath the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of this life, and of that which is to come,</hi> and thereby ſhal all mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters be bleſſed vnto vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Of all men they are the husbands, that labour moſt for grace.</note>Seeing therfore they that ſpend their paines in ſeeking of grace, ſhall neuer loſe their labour, nor miſſe of their marke, but alwayes obtaine that which they do deſire, and when once they haue poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of it, it will abide with them, they cannot loſe it though they would, it is ſo durable and perma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:7856:100"/> that it will neuer decay, and ſo vnited and ingrafted into the nature of the parties, that it can by no poſſible meanes bee wholly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away; and therefore as in other things, ſo in this, the continuance of it addes greatly vnto the worth of it,<note place="margin">1. Pet<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 4.</note> for grace is a perpetuall inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance that farre ſurpaſſeth al that the world can affoord: a man muſt leaue all his earthly inheritance and aboundance hee knoweth not how ſoone, neither can his great pompe deſcend into the graue with him, neither can he ſo make it ouer vnto his ſeed,<note place="margin">Pſal. 49.17.</note> but that they may bee defrauded of it; but the heauenly treaſure is ours whiles we liue, and when we die, and after death, yea at, and after the reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction for euermore: and as the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuitie, ſo alſo the excellency of this in it owne nature ſhould bee
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:7856:101"/> a forcible motiue vnto vs, and ſet an edge vpon our affections to purſue after it continually, for whereas other things are dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and hurtfull,<note place="margin">Godlineſſe is profitable in this life, and in the life to come</note> this is alwayes profitable and helpfull, it maketh vs bleſſed in this preſent life, and in the life to come; it bringeth with it the comfort of the ſpirit, the feeling of Gods loue and fauour, and the comfortable vſe of all outward good things, wee are not likely, at leaſt not certaine to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue here many dayes, and what an vnſpeakeable comfort then is it to be aſſured that when wee go fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men wee ſhall goe to God, and when we leaue the earth,<note place="margin">Though man ſhould forſake vs, yet God will not leaue vs comfortles.</note> we ſhall inherit heauen, that we ſhall haue peace at our death, and glory after our death: if the peſtilence enter into our houſes, or take hold on our perſons, when none dare come
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:7856:101"/> vnto vs, then God will be with vs, though our bodyes bee infected, yet our ſoules can neuer bee ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, if wee haue grace in our hearts, but that God dareth to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into our houſes to viſit vs, and when our ſoules ſhall bee parted from our bodyes, he will not think it too much to giue them a place of reſt with himſelfe in his owne kingdome, and at length vnite them to our bodies againe, that they may enioy euerlaſting bliſſe together, this <hi>generation of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous ſhall be bleſſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, therefore ſeeing religion is ſuch an incomparable treaſure,<note place="margin">True pietie is the onely meanes to reforme our crooked wayes.</note> this ſhould teach vs to haue the meanes in due eſtimation, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we may bee made truly religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, by which our mindes that are blinde may bee enlightened, our hearts of crooked may bee
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:7856:102"/> made ſtraight, of prowd may bee made humble, and of fraudulent may be made true and faithfull; &amp; thoſe meanes are the word and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, prayer &amp; the like, which are ſteps whereby we muſt aſcend vnto this honourable eſtate, for it is as poſſible for men to make ſtayres to climbe vp into the skie, as for vs without theſe to aſcend vnto heauen by any deuices of our owne framing.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The word of God preached is the chiefeſt meanes to looſe vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bonds of ſinne and ſathan.</note>Secondly, the word is the key that muſt open hell gates to ſet vs at liberty from the bonds of ſinne, of ſathan, and of death, and to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locke heauen gates that wee may haue entrance into glory, in which reſpect it is, that Chriſt ſayth vnto <hi>Peter,</hi> that he would giue vnto him, and conſequently to all mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Goſpel, the keyes of the kingdome of heauen; that is,
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:7856:102"/> the diſpenſation of the word &amp; ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, which maketh the way into heauen lie open to all ſuch as by faith receiue the ſame into their hearts, ſo that we ſhould not come vnto the meanes with a baſe conceit or light eſtimation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, but with a large and ample de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire and exſpectation of taking be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite thereby; if men can once e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpy away how they may riſe in the world, either in great wealth or promotion, they will bee moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrious and laborious in that courſe, they will refuſe no paines in ſeed time, though the weather be vnſeaſonable &amp; cold, and their worke euery way troubleſome, but they will put themſelues to it with all care and induſtry, in hope though it bee but an vncertaine hope of bettering their eſtate, ſo thoſe that liue by fayres and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets,
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:7856:103"/> will not faile one of them or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily, neither heate nor cold, winde nor raine, nor any the like impediments ſhall hinder them from purſuing the commodity, &amp; why then ſhould we be negligent and play the ſluggards while our ſeede-time laſteth, and the Lord biddeth vs plow vp the fallow ground of our hearts,<note place="margin">Ierem. 4.</note> that he may ſow therein the ſeed of life, which will neuer faile to yeeld vs a plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull harueſt if wee can wait vpon him for the ſame? and why ſhould we be ſlacke and careleſſe when our chiefe market dayes and faire dayes come, and not rather ſet our hearts and endeuours to ſeeke af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thoſe things, which all that ſeeke ſhall finde, and being found will make vs bleſſed for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more?</p>
               <p>Therefore wee ought to breake
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:7856:103"/> through all impediments, and ſwallow vp al difficulties with the conſideration of this, that our iourny tendeth not to the getting of ſome ſmall commoditie, or to the purchaſing of ſome worldly poſſeſſions, but that we are trauel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling towards our owne countrey, where we ſhall receiue an inualua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and eternall crowne of glory: and albeit we muſt paſſe through many rough &amp; craggy and thor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wayes, and meete with ſundry things that will be very irkeſome and vnpleaſant,<note place="margin">The defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of the way ſhould not hinder vs.</note> yet let vs make ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count with all, that we ſhall finde many ſweee comforts, and ioyes vnſpeakeable and glorious, in the midſt of our pilgrimages and in the end ſhall haue the fruition of that bleſſedneſſe which will make amends for all.</p>
               <p>Now that our deſires may bee
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:7856:104"/> futher enlarged towards heauen, and our affections the better with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawne from the loue of this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull life, and world of vanities, let vs meditate on thoſe compleat ioyes, which no tongue indeed is able to expreſſe, or heart of man conceiue, for if their eſtate bee ſo bleſſed in this life, what ſhall their happineſſe bee when they depart out of this life,<note place="margin">The happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the life to come</note> to haue the fruition of thoſe ioyes which are prepared for the Saints in the kingdome of glory, where all teares ſhall be wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped away from their eyes, &amp; they being altogether freed from ſinne and ſorrow, ſhall receiue an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall crowne of bleſſedneſſe with the Saints and Angels in Gods owne preſence, where is ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Ioy,<note place="margin">Pſal. 16.11.</note> and <hi>at whoſe right hand are pleaſures for euermore.</hi> Therefore I may ſay with the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle,
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:7856:104"/> 
                  <hi>no eye hath ſeene, no eare hath heard, neither hath it entred into the heart of man,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.9.</note> 
                  <hi>what vnſpeakeable ioyes God hath prepared for them that loue him.</hi> If it be ſo ſayth an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Father, what can I doe elſe, but lift vp mine eyes to heauen, mine eares to God, and my heart to Paradiſe, to ſee and vnderſtand what I can comprehend vpon earth; and therfore my ſoule long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth after thee O God, and ſigheth till it ſee the brightneſſe of thy face, O kingdome of euerlaſting bliſſe, where thou O Lord, the hope of all Saints art, reioycing them on euery ſide with thy bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſight. If the wiſe men of the Eaſt came ſo farre off, and reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to ſee Chriſt in the manger. What will it be in the ſight of his elect to ſee him in his glory? If <hi>Iohn</hi> Baptiſt a babe ſprang in his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:7856:105"/> wombe for ioy of Chriſt ſo newly conceiued, &amp; not yet ſeene. What ſhall his reall preſence doe in his royall kingdome, but euen rauiſh with ioy our very hearts &amp; ſoules, when we ſhall continually enioy his moſt glorious ſight, for it paſſeth all other glory that the Saints haue in heauen, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the beames of glory from the brightneſſe of his Maieſtie. If <hi>Salomons</hi> ſeruants were accounted happy (of <hi>Sheha</hi> the Southerne queene) for their dayly liuing in the Court of <hi>Salomon,</hi> &amp; hearing of his wiſedome, how happy then and thrice bleſſed ſhall the Saints and ſeruants of God bee accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that liue continually in the Court of heauen, the very para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe and Pallace of God himſelfe? O how happy and bleſſed is hee which with the onely deſire and
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:7856:105"/> loue of eternitie pineth away; ſuch a one is neither prowde with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie, nor caſt downe with ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſitie, for as he hath nothing in this world that hee loueth, ſo is there no loſſe of any thing in this life that he feareth. Sweete is the fountaine to the weary traueller, and reſt to the tyred ſeruant; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable is the coole euening after a hot Sunny day; yet much more ſweet will it be to the Saints of this heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly citie to haue peace after warre, pleaſure after paine, ioy after trouble, and conſtant ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie after their ſo long endured ſorrowes, then ſhall we bleſſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed as here the Prophet ſayth.</p>
               <p>If one Sunne can lighten and fill the whole world with his brightneſſe,<note place="margin">Dan. 3.12. Mat. 13 43</note> what ſhall ſo many glorified bodies of the bleſſed ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, that ſhall bee as ſo many
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:7856:106"/> Sunnes, ſo many Lampes, and ſo many ſhining Lights in heauen? then ſhall we bleſſed indeed, when we ſhall be like vnto God,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.2. 1. Cor. 13.</note> which by nature is bleſſed, and we ſhall bee like vnto God when we ſhall ſee him as he is; for this only ſight of God is our whole happineſſe. O what a ioy ſhall it bee when at one view, wee ſhall behold the moſt high and hidden myſtery of the inſeparable Trinity, and of the loue of God therein: then ſhall mans minde haue perpetuall reſt and peace, neither ſhall it deſire a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny further vnderſtanding, when he hath all before his eyes, that may be vnderſtood, then ſhall mans will bee quiet, when hee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyeth that felicitie, wherein all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good things, as in the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of all happineſſe are contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, then ſhall faith haue her per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:7856:106"/> worke, and hope ſhall enioy that which ſhee long deſired; but charity ſhall endure for euer: then ſhall bee ſung continuall prayſes vnto the Lambe,<note place="margin">Reu. 14.3.</note> and the ſong (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be alwayes ſong) yet it ſhall be euer new, the ioy, mirrh, melody, pleaſure, power, wealth, riches, honour, beauty, fellowſhip dainties, odors, glory, wiſedome, knowledge, treaſure, ſecurities, peace, quietneſſe, and eternall fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitie, is beyond al vnderſtanding and comprehenſion of man which the faithfull ſhall haue and enioy world without end, with God the Father, the Sonne, and the holy Ghoſt, with Angels, and Arch-Angels, Patriarkes and Prophets, with the Apoſtles &amp; Euangeliſts, with the Martyrs and Confeſſors, and with the Saints of God, in the pallace of the Lord in heauen,
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:7856:107"/> there ſhall bee an euerlaſting Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baoth, which no euening ſhal end, then ſhall the geneartion of the righteous bee fully bleſſed.</p>
               <p>There we ſhall reſt, and we ſhal ſee,<note place="margin">No content but in the kingdome of heauen.</note> we ſhall ſee, and we ſhall loue; we ſhall loue, and we ſhall praiſe. Behold, ſaith <hi>Auguſtine, That which is the end, is without end:</hi> For what other end is there ordained for the godly, but to attaine to that Kingdome wich hath no end. Wee call Paradiſe our Country, and the Patriarkes our Fathers; and the Saints our brethren and friends. Why runne we not then with all ſpeede to enioy our coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and ſalute our Parents? a great number of our friends and kinsfolkes, brethren and children, doe there attend, wiſhing and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting our comming, what ioy
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:7856:107"/> will it bee both to them and vs, there to meete one another? what pleaſures are there amongſt the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of heauen, which now feare death no more, and are ſure to liue for euer?<note place="margin">Thoſe whoſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings are darkened, cannot ſee their happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note> Wo to the blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our eyes that ſee not this, woe to the deafneſſe of our eares that heare not this in ſuch wiſe as a we ſhould doe, where through we might be ſo farre from fearing death, that rather we ſhould wiſh it, with old <hi>Simeon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 2.29.</note> 
                  <hi>Now let thy ſeruant depart in peace:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 42.2.</note> and with <hi>Dauid, when ſhall I come and appeare before thee,</hi> that we may be bleſſed for euermore.</p>
               <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">If true faith were placed in our hearts, feare would va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh away.</note> if true knowledge and faith poſſeſt our hearts as they ſhould, feare and doubtfulneſſe would vanquiſh quite away, for aſſurance of heauenly things, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vs willing to part with earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:7856:108"/> he cannot contemne this life that knoweth not the other, if wee would deſpiſe this world, we muſt thinke of the glorious life that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth it, and if wee can endure paine for health, much more ſhould wee abide a few pangs for glory, how fooliſh are we to feare a vanquiſhed enemy? Chriſt hath triumphed ouer death, it bleedeth (as it were) and gaſpeth vnder vs,<note place="margin">Death be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, wee ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to bee diſſolued, &amp; to be with Chriſt.</note> &amp; yet do we tremble, it is enough that Chriſt dyed, neither would he haue dyed, but that we might dye with ſafety and pleaſure: how true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly may we ſay of this our <hi>Dauid,</hi> thou art worth ten thouſand of vs, yea, worth a world of Angels, yet he dyed for vs; who would there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore liue that knowes his Sauiour dyed? Who can be a Chriſtian, and would not bee like him, that would not dye after him? let vs
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:7856:108"/> thinke of this, and iudge whether all the world can hire vs to die.</p>
               <p>But (alas) great is our vnbeliefe, full faint and weake is our faith, or elſe night and day, teares and cries ſhould bee our meate and drinke, whilſt the wicked ſay vnto vs, <hi>Where is now your God?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 42.3.</note> We ſhould wiſh rather to be doore-keepers in the houſe of God,<note place="margin">Pſal. 84.10.</note> then to dwell in theſe vngodly tents: <hi>For one day in his Courts, is better then a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand:</hi> it is a token of little loue to God, to be ſo loath to goe vnto him when hee calleth, herein wee ought to lament the weakeneſſe of our faith, and ſeeing our wants to prepare for remedy againſt the time of neede, and to beg of God his aide, ſtrength and comfort a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the pinch: which things vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtly if we aske in faith, we ſhall obtaine and find his promiſe true:
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:7856:109"/> God reacheth out his hand to conduct vs, but wee draw backe our owne, and runne away when hee calleth vs, if hee bring vs into the way of ſaluation, wee mourne for the World, and we looke behinde vs with Lots Wife, and hinder our deſire of well doing, wee muſt therefore rouze vp ourſelues, and not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine ſtill in the mire, we muſt be fortified in this vertue, who ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth and comforteth vs in all diſtreſſe.</p>
               <p>Laſtly to conclude, let vs at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to deſpiſe corruptible things, and to deſire heauenly and eternall, when God calleth at eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry occaſion, let vs hearken vnto him: if he be our Guide, we muſt follow him: for to arriue in his houſe, let vs receiue his benefit, and himſelfe too, for hee giues
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:7856:109"/> himſelfe vnto vs in the perſon of his ſonne, hee cauſeth vs to ſee the meanes how to come vnto him; wee muſt therefore requeſt him to beſtow vpon vs will and deſire, to come thither by Faith, Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, Hope, &amp;c. And that hee would mainetaine his gifts and graces in vs, to the end that heere wee may mourne in this mortall life, and attend in the aſſurance of his mercy, for the end of this world and our laſt day, which ſhal bee the beginning of our true life, when wee are to receiue an inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, not mortall but immortall; not earthly, but heauenly; not like the Goord of <hi>Ionas,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ionas 4.7.</note> but the Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of <hi>Libans;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 8.4.</note> not like the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in <hi>Egypt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 3.7.</note> but in the <hi>Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes;</hi> not like the morning dew, but the waters of Paradiſe;<note place="margin">Epheſ. 6.16.</note> not A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prons of Fig-leaues, but the Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:7856:110" rendition="simple:additions"/> of ſaluation;<note place="margin">Gen. 5.14.</note> not like <hi>Iacobs</hi> Pottage which hee ſold, but the birth-right which hee bought;<note place="margin">2. King. 2.11</note> not a Tabernacle, but a Temple; not time, but eternity; not like an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bortiue child, but like <hi>Henoch</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> which neuer taſted of death, beſeeching God our heauenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for his ſonne Chriſt his ſake, to keepe vs ſoules and bodies to his kingdome and glory; and to leade vs, order vs, and diſpoſe of vs as he will, in all things, in all places, and for euer; that at the length we may come whether wee would; that is, into his owne bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed preſence, and fruition of immortality with Chriſt and his Saints, world with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out end. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:7856:110"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
